<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Shrama</title>
    <link>https://raunackt.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Shrama</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Raunack Tripathi</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 13:58:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raunackt.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Āryīkarṇa of Writing: Alkanes</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/011-aryikarna-alkanes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 10:30:51 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/011-aryikarna-alkanes/</guid>
      <description>I have previously discussed some obstacles and some preliminary propositions of mine that I think will be useful in such culture-building. In case you do not want to go through all of it or just need a refresher, the key-points I made were:
We are going up against centuries of development of Western formal systems, so the process is going to be slow
Translating words or concepts one-to-one is not only not possible, it is also undesirable unless the translation is oragnic</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have previously discussed some <a href="https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/006-aryikarana-of-writing/">obstacles</a> and some <a href="https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/007-aryikarana-of-writing-dvi/">preliminary propositions</a> of mine that I think will be useful in such culture-building. In case you do not want to go through all of it or just need a refresher, the key-points I made were:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>We are going up against centuries of development of Western formal systems, so the process is going to be slow</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Translating words or concepts one-to-one is not only not possible, it is also undesirable unless the translation is oragnic</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>We have to build a system, instead of translating/transforming concepts as they come, so that our descendants will use such a system to write/compose when they have newer realizations of knowledge</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>In the previous blog I present the First Part of the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus to illustrate a point. In this blog, I am going to provide my attempts at <em>āryīkaraṇa</em> of nomenclature of alkanes. Why did choose alkanes specifically? No reason really. It seemed like a low-hanging fruit. While I was thinking that IUPAC nomenclature, which helps in naming different structures of hydrocarbons, would provide a good ground for flexing the strength of <em>saṅskṛta</em>, I am not going to change (or think of changing) the naming rules. Rather, I have focused on just providing <em>saṅskṛta</em> names for existing alkanes. From there, one can use the IUPAC nomenclature to construct names of such structures in <em>saṅskṛta</em>. Also, for now these are just restricted to alkyls and alkanes, not alkenes or alkalines (latter of which may have <em>saṅskṛta</em> names already). I will be discussing my approach and rationale to choosing the names I did, and hope that the reader focuses on the principle of <em>āryīkaraṇa</em> rather than the actual result. But let me not make excuses this early. I have used <a href="https://ashtadhyayi.com/">ashtadhyayi.com</a> and <a href="https://www.etymonline.com/">online etymology dictionary</a> as resources.</p>
<h2 id="approach-and-rationale-for-_saṅskṛta_-names">Approach and Rationale for <em>Saṅskṛta</em> names</h2>
<p>Besides what I have discussed in my previous blogs (summarized at the top here), I keep three more things in mind while attempting to write the <em>saṅskṛta</em> names for non-<em>saṅskṛta</em> or non-Hindu concepts (meaning, which were either not found by Hindu-s or simply do not have <em>saṅskṛta</em> names):</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Is a direct translation feasible?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Can a name be ascribed based on unique properties or attributes of the object in question?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Does it make sense to name an object after the place it was found/invented provided it is in the bounds of the Indian subcontinent?</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I will refrain from talking about every single decision I have made in my process here, but for starters I have used the 2nd approach for the most part in this scenario. This is because research on alkanes has been going on for centuries. Let us just take one example of Methane (CH4). <a href="https://www.etymonline.com/word/methane">Etymologically</a>, methane is coined by adding &ldquo;-ane&rdquo; to &ldquo;meth&rdquo; from &ldquo;methyl&rdquo;. Furthermore, methyl <a href="https://www.etymonline.com/word/methyl">comes from</a> the Greek words &ldquo;methy&rdquo; and &ldquo;hyle&rdquo;, which means wood-wine. This is apparently because methyl was observed in wood-alcohol.</p>
<p>If we were to use the direct translation approach, we would end up with काष्ठमधु (<em>kāṣṭhamadhu</em>) or काष्ठमद्यम् (<em>kāṣṭhamadyam</em>) or something similar, which just feels extremely awkward and will never make sense to us because we do not have a history of methyl(/methylene) converting to methane by a slow process. For this very reason, we also cannot try and name methane or methyl after a place from Indian subcontinent, because we have no records that our ancestors observed anything like this. So, the only option is to try and name methane and methyl based on their unique properties. Considering that the group of all these gases are colorless, odorless and combustible, we can probably use some words in <em>saṅskṛta</em> that carry the same meanings. I have focused on the combustible property of these gases. I did not focus on colorless and odorless because that is a lack of an attribute, and using words likes अवर्ण (<em>avarṇa</em>) or अगन्ध (<em>agandha</em>) felt weird for words that will be used in a system. Of course, some of this will come down to preferance of the person working on such a process, I do not see any reason why this would be undesirable, since we are going to fill in holes. I have used the word दाह (<em>dāha</em>) for combustible/flammable. One can probably use दाहक (<em>dāhaka</em>) too, but I used the one with fewer <em>akṣara</em>-s. Following this, I will use दाह as a suffix for all names of the alkane gases.</p>
<p>The first four gases &ndash; methane, ethane, propane and butane have some history attached to them, but from pentane to decane, the suffix &ldquo;-ane&rdquo; is added to the word for numbers. I have applied a similar principle, but for all the 10 gases. Meaning, methane to butane also have quantifiers attached to them before दाह. To put it simply, the prefix &ldquo;प्र&rdquo; (<em>pra</em>) implies forward/first/before in <em>saṅskṛta</em>, and since methane is the &ldquo;first&rdquo; gas in the alkane group, I have called methane प्रदाह (<em>pradāha</em>). As a clarification, प्रदाह is already a formal word in <em>saṅskṛta</em> and <a href="https://ashtadhyayi.com/kosha?search=%E0%A4%AA%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%A6%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%B9">means</a> burning/heating/consuming, but we need not worry about overlapping meanings or pre-existing words &ndash; <em>saṅskṛta</em> words can have contextual meanings. Ask <a href="https://i.imgflip.com/1cf8by.jpg?a473880">anyone</a> who has tried to read the <em>dharmashāstra</em>-s. Following this naming scheme, here are the names for 10 gases:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center">Latin name</th>
<th style="text-align:center"><em>Saṅskṛta nāma</em></th>
<th style="text-align:center">Transliteration</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Methane</td>
<td style="text-align:center">प्रदाह</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>pradāha</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Ethane</td>
<td style="text-align:center">द्वयदाह</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>dvayadāha</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Propane</td>
<td style="text-align:center">त्रयदाह</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>trayadāha</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Butane</td>
<td style="text-align:center">कृतदाह</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>kṛtadāha</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Pentane</td>
<td style="text-align:center">पञ्चदाह​</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>paṅcadāha</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Hexane</td>
<td style="text-align:center">षोडाह</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>ṣoḍāha</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Heptane</td>
<td style="text-align:center">सप्तदाह</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>saptadāha</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Octane</td>
<td style="text-align:center">अष्टदाह</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>aṣṭadāha</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Nonane</td>
<td style="text-align:center">नवदाह</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>navadāha</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Decane</td>
<td style="text-align:center">दशदाह</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>dashadāha</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>IUPAC nomenclature also uses the alkyl groups, so we would require their <em>saṅskṛta</em> names too. From a very reductionist prespective, an alkyl is a just one order lower than an alkane. <strong>This is not the actual case</strong>, but I have gone with this understanding for now. Considering this, I have used the prefix of &ldquo;उप&rdquo; (<em>upa</em>) meaning substitute/lower/secondary or something similar with the quantifies for the <em>dāha</em>-s. As with the alkanes, the alkyl names will be the following:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center">Latin name</th>
<th style="text-align:center"><em>Saṅskṛta nāma</em></th>
<th style="text-align:center">Transliteration</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Methyl</td>
<td style="text-align:center">उपप्र</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>upapra</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Ethyl</td>
<td style="text-align:center">उपद्वय</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>upadvaya</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Propyl</td>
<td style="text-align:center">उपत्रय</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>upatraya</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Butyl</td>
<td style="text-align:center">उपकृत</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>upakṛta</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Pentyl</td>
<td style="text-align:center">उपपञ्च​</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>upapaṅca</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Hexyl</td>
<td style="text-align:center">उपषष्</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>upaṣaṣ</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Heptyl</td>
<td style="text-align:center">उपसप्त</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>upasapta</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Octyl</td>
<td style="text-align:center">उपाष्ट</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>upāṣṭa</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Nonyl</td>
<td style="text-align:center">उपनव</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>upanava</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">Decyl</td>
<td style="text-align:center">उपदश</td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>upadasha</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>As mentioned earlier, I have not attempted to come up with any new naming rules or tweaked the existing IUPAC rules, it simply does not seem worth it. I will hence be following the IUPAC nomenclature.</p>
<p>I would have loved to illustrate the chain-diagrams for the hydrocarbon structures of these alkanes, but I simply cannot at the moment. I will however write them out (hope you remember some organic chemistry lmao):</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>2-methylepentane &ndash; २-उपप्रपञ्चदाह​</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>2,3-dimethylbutane &ndash; २,३-द्विउपप्रकृतदाह</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>2-ethyl 3,4,6-trimethyloctane &ndash; २-उपद्वय ३,४,६-त्रिउपप्राष्टदाह</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Again, apologies if this is not immediately clear, but I promise if you draw out different strucutes and use the <em>saṅskṛta</em> names, it will work and feel natural.</p>
<h2 id="_saṅskṛta_-writeup"><em>Saṅskṛta</em> writeup:</h2>
<p>It only makes sense that we now try and see how this would work in full-<em>saṅskṛta</em> writing. So here is a small write-up that discusses the same concepts:</p>





<pre tabindex="0"><code>पञ्च द्रव्येषु वायुः अस्ति 
वायवे तन्मात्रौ शब्द स्पर्श च
वायौ विभिन्न वर्गाः सन्ति
एकं वर्गं दाहकवातम्  इति 
दाहकवाताः अग्नि प्राप्त्वा दहन्ति 
वयं आपाङ्गारस्य जन्म दाहकवातस्य चर्चा करिष्यामः 
आपस्य अङ्गारस्य च संधि आपाङ्गार इति
एकं अङ्गारस्य अणुः चतुः आपस्य अणवः च प्रदाह इति नाम दाहकवातम् जनयति
प्रदाहम् आङ्ग्लभाषायाम् मेथेन इति उच्यते
एतत् प्रथम दाहकवातम् अतः प्रदाह
एक अङ्गार अणेः सन्धिबल चतुः अस्ति
परन्तु किञ्चित् उपवाताः भवति ये तेषाम् आपाङ्गारेभ्यः एक आप अणुः न्यूनाः दधन्ति
वयं एतानि उपवातेभ्यः उप इति उपसर्गम्  उपयोगं करिष्यामः च आपाङ्गाराणाम् शब्दानाम् प्रथम पदे संधि करिष्यामः
अतः प्रस्तुत सूचि प्राप्नोसि प्रदाह उपप्र च द्वयडह उपद्वाय च इत्यादि</code></pre><p>For clarifications: वातः (<em>vātaḥ</em>) is used for &ldquo;gas&rdquo;, आपाङ्गारम् (<em>āpāṅgāram</em>) is used for hydrocarbon (as of this writing, I have not decided a name for carbon) and सन्धिबलम्/बलम् is used for <a href="https://www.etymonline.com/word/valence">valence</a>, because interestingly valence is derived from PIE root &ldquo;*wal-&rdquo;, meaning &ldquo;to be strong&rdquo;, which is just <em>saṅskṛta</em> बल् (<em>bal</em>), meaning the same (a scenario in which direct translation works perfectly). The opening <em>vākya</em>-s have been taken from <em>vaisheṣika darshana</em>. Now, the time for excuses.</p>
<h2 id="clarifications">Clarifications</h2>
<p>I am not a chemist, neither am I entirely proficient in <em>saṅskṛta</em>. There could be several errors in this blog, relating to my knowledge of chemistry. Also several typos and grammatical errors relating to <em>saṅskṛta</em>, so I do not encourage people to take the technical parts as facts and also that I view myself as a part of such <em>āryīkaraṇa</em> &ndash; I will more be than happy if someone creates a better system than mine, more intuitive words to use than what I have provided, while fixing my mistakes. This is not supposed to be a personal project, rather a long-term process that must be discussed at the highest levels of culture so that scholars from various fields can put forth their assertions. But I will consider my efforts fulfilled if someone is merely inspired by this, to vastly improve on it, and push forward more that anyone else currently. Or, maybe you can come with new names entirely, that do not follow any convention and each alkane, each alkyl have a distinct name altogether. Whatever ends up happening, I hope these efforts are sensible in some way, however small.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On reading the Dharmashāstra-s</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/010-on-reading-ds/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 10:32:33 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/010-on-reading-ds/</guid>
      <description>Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about it:
How to not read the dharmashāstra-s I find it amusing when people add &amp;ldquo;interested in dharma&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;, usually pairing it with other interests and hobbies of theirs, in bios or description on social media platforms of their accounts. I do not point this out as a flaw, but the implications of such descriptions tend to reduce dharma to a hobby or an intellectual exercise, completely ignoring the part where dharma is meant to be followed, as in your day-to-day actions, and hence is not merely something to be thought of or read about, but something that must be practiced actively.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ok, let&rsquo;s talk about it:</p>
<h2 id="how-to-not-read-the-_dharmashāstra_-s">How to <strong>not</strong> read the <em>dharmashāstra</em>-s</h2>
<p>I find it amusing when people  add &ldquo;interested in <em>dharma</em>&hellip;&rdquo;, usually pairing it with other interests and hobbies of theirs, in bios or description on social media platforms of their accounts. I do not point this out as a flaw, but the implications of such descriptions tend to reduce <em>dharma</em> to a hobby or an intellectual exercise, completely ignoring the part where <em>dharma</em> is meant to be followed, as in your day-to-day actions, and hence is not merely something to be thought of or read about, but something that must be practiced actively. The reason I do not call this a flaw is because obviously such people are not a monolith entity who all share the same meaning of &ldquo;interested in&ndash;&rdquo; and might very well be great practisioners of <em>dharma</em>. But my average experience has been otherwise.</p>
<p>There is a general apathy in practicing <em>dharma</em>, and I am a bit stringent on this part in that I mean actually practicing your <em>varṇadharma</em> in the areas where you can. Since people want <em>dharma</em> to be relevant in some fashion, there is an emphasis on reading more about <em>dharma</em>, which is a little too much for my liking. <em>&ldquo;What is the Bhagavadgītā saying about varṇa by birth?&rdquo;</em>, <em>&ldquo;what is the Manusmṛti saying about the status of a Shūdra?&rdquo;</em>, <em>&ldquo;what does Rāma say while exiling Sītā?&rdquo;</em>, among others are some of the mainstream discussions about the <em>dharmashāstra</em>-s that focus on the non-critical points of the scriptures. I call it &ldquo;non-critical&rdquo; because such questions do not help in one&rsquo;s practice and only until a few centuries ago, people were deriving completely different learnings from the same <em>shāstra</em>-s, instead of looking at them from a &ldquo;pragmatic&rdquo;, social-welfare-esque perspective. Also because of these discussions, a person who wants to explore <em>dharma</em> through the <em>shāstra</em>-s would know more about the non-critical parts like whether or not <em>varṇa</em> is by birth and why should oil be poured in a Shūdra&rsquo;s ear if he hears <em>vedapāṭha</em>. Hence, the cycle of intellectual, democratized, irrelevant opinions continue flowing into more apathy and hatred for <em>dharma</em> or for the more narcissistic of us, the ideas of &ldquo;reforming&rdquo; <em>dharma</em>. Due to this, the focus on actually performing <em>dhārmika kārya</em>-s only suffers.</p>
<p>I do not think it fruitful, or even necessary to discuss <strong>why</strong> such a phenomenon exists now. You can actually blame everyone here, since this cannot a be work of a single entity, even though there might be a catalyst, but rather such degeneration has been going on for a good century or more. I think it is much better if we discuss why <em>shāstra</em>-s should be studied to only improve our understanding of <em>dharma</em> in order to practice it. I think it is also crucial that I emphasize that you cannot attain any <em>siddhi</em> just because you understood what Kṛṣṇa said in Bhagavadgītā. And that it is entirely irrevelant what Manu says about a status of a Shūdra because that is not what historically happened, not because it was a non-adherence to Manusmṛti, but because people knew what adhering to a <em>dharmashāstra</em> actually meant.</p>
<h2 id="why-read-the-_dharmashāstra_-s">Why read the <em>dharmashāstra</em>-s?</h2>
<p>You see, we are a culture that has always had numerous intellectuals giving their inputs. Some were accepted others were discarded. This is not probably an intended attribute of the civilization by the ṛṣi-s, but something that ended up happening because of multitudes of ideas about society, individual and just different subjects of study existing all throughout history. Manu, a king, is expected to know more about a social organization and law enforcement than say, a Yājñavalkya who is a master of <em>adhyātma</em>. Of course, both of these have overlapped and <em>varṇāshrama</em> can only be understood with the underlying ontology of Veda-s, but here is where the multiplicity of opinions comes into being. So while everyone agrees that <em>dharma</em> is supreme, they might recommend different ways to practice and implement <em>dharma</em>. Luckily for me, such is exactly the <a href="https://www.wisdomlib.org/hinduism/book/manusmriti-with-the-commentary-of-medhatithi/d/doc145588.html">teaching</a> of Manu himself:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>श्रुतिद्वैधं तु यत्र स्यात् तत्र धर्मावुभौ स्मृतौ। उभावपि हि तौ धर्मौ सम्यगुक्तौ मनीषिभिः॥</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Where there is conflict between two Vedic texts, both are held to be Dharma; both have been rightly pronounced by the wise to be Dharma.&rdquo;</p>
<p>And it needn&rsquo;t mean that only following <em>varṇadharma</em> is hundred percent required &ndash; I do not have a heart of stone, you know. There is the <em>sāmānya dharma</em> of being truthful, humble, donating to the poor and learned, honoring the ancestors and praying to <em>devatā</em>-s, mainting cleanliness and other things that can be followed by everyone irrespective of their status. It is just that such <em>sāmānya dharma</em> can be directed into <em>varṇadharma</em> and different people of different statuses follow different rituals. Additionally, one is not expected to learn about <em>dharma</em> directly from the <em>shāstra</em>-s as far as practice is concerned. Different <em>kārya</em>-s like <em>dhyāna</em>, <em>jāpa</em>, <em>ghaṇapāṭha</em>, etc., are physical actions that are learnt only through the guidance of a father or a <em>guru</em>. Hence, your family or your <em>guru</em> is also the source of information for not only such <em>nityakarma</em>-s but also all the stories from <em>purāṇa</em>-s. As much as this was the mainstream in the last few centuries, I do not expect people to study under a <em>guru</em>, in a <em>gurukula</em> or send their children either. But <em>dharmashāstra</em>-s are accessible online, so that is where most people are going to flock to. Irrespective of this fact, the intention to read the <em>dharmashāstra</em>-s must not change, i.e., continuous practice. So, to sum it up, the answer to &ldquo;why should you read <em>dharmashāstra</em>-s&rdquo; should be to practice <em>dharma</em> daily. Has that been drilled into your head yet?</p>
<h2 id="how-to-actually-read-the-_dharmashāstra_-s">How to actually read the <em>dharmashāstra</em>-s</h2>
<p>With the intetions now clear (hopefully), we shall discuss the <strong>how</strong>. This does not mean that there is any actual process or <em>vidhi</em>, even though Manu does suggest various <a href="https://www.wisdomlib.org/hinduism/book/manusmriti-with-the-commentary-of-medhatithi/d/doc199527.html">rules of studying</a> like the proper attire and the direction one must face. I think such regulations can be eased out a little for now. Of course, it is better if you can commit to these, but if you cannot, then read it with the same respect and diligence anyway.</p>
<p>A trend among those seeking <em>dharma</em> through <em>shāstra</em>-s is directly jumping to reading the Bhagavadgītā. For those who would not be aware, Bhagavadgītā is a part of Mahābhārata, and the Bhagavadgītā read separately specifically starts from the 23rd chapter of the larger Bhagavadgītā <em>upaparva</em> in Bhīṣma <em>parva</em>. It begins with Arjuna asking Kṛṣṇa to bring their chariot in the middle of the battlefield of Kurukṣetra and then refuses to kill his relatives. Now, most people, and specifically the people whose first proper reading of a Hindu scripture is Bhagavadgītā, completely miss out on the emotional weight of Arjuna&rsquo;s <em>viṣāda</em> here. Sure, you can probably understand why Arjuna is sad and dejected, by placing yourself in his position, but you would not know who Arjuna himself is.</p>
<p>Arjuna is the only person during the events of Mahābhārata who has remained victorious in every encounter he has had (except against Rudra but that is too tall an order). Arjuna has faced the most dire of conditions and emerged triumphant. He has always been on the backfoot, but manages to cut down the obstacles with his dexterity and bravery. This is your protagonist, you follow his journey for thousands of <em>shloka</em>-s before reaching this moment. In fact, Arjuna&rsquo;s dejection is outright hypocritical because once Pāṇḍava-s were done with their exile, Arjuna was in full favor of a war, while Yuddhiṣṭhira and Bhīma &ndash; BHĪMA OF ALL PEOPLE &ndash; were against the war! Such things may have been covered in the <em>bhāṣya</em>-s by the <em>ācārya</em>-s but there is huge difference between just reading a short summary of these and actually having followed Arjuna at every step and then seeing him dejected. Arjuna being the best of men, his dejection is not merely his own but a loss of confidence of all mankind. It is with all this context that Bhagavān starts motivating and instructing him about his <em>dharma</em>. Arjuna&rsquo;s dejection is useless, because ultimately everything will die, either at the hands of Arjuna or Bhagavān himself. Neither is this a case for nihillism because you are responsible for making a world in which everyone gets <em>mukti</em> from wretched <em>saṅsāra</em>. And this is only possible if you channel your <em>dharma</em> through <em>varṇāshrama</em>. How many people who read Bhagavadgītā in isolation from rest of Mahābhārata can really claim to understand what <em>varṇāshrama</em> is? Bhagavān&rsquo;s instructions are extremely direct, with <em>ācārya</em>-s having written elaborate commentaries on them to explain how it meshes with the larger <em>dharma</em>. And on this note, just because <em>ācārya</em>-s wrote on Bhagavadgītā separately gives <strong>us</strong> no excuse to follow them in reading it. Of course, the <em>ācārya</em>-s would have read Mahābhārata, along with other <em>purāṇa</em>-s, <em>smṛti</em>-s and the <em>upaniṣad</em>-s before offering any opinion of their&rsquo;s even on a single <em>akṣara</em>. Bhagavān&rsquo;s instructions are only the theory when it comes to following <em>dharma</em>. Bhagavān does not really go into the <strong>how</strong> side of things. He just lays out the duties of all the people and <strong>why</strong> is following these important. The <strong>how</strong> is answered in Shānti and Anushāsana <em>parva</em>-s of Mahābhārata. <em>Varṇāshrama</em> is deeply reflected upon in these <em>parva</em>-s, covering many different scenarios and stories of the ancients. It is these <em>parva</em>-s that actually compel you to act, and commit to the actions, while Bhagavān&rsquo;s precepts justify such actions at an extremely deep level. Bhagavadgītā does not encourage you to visit <em>tīrtha</em>-s, or talk about reconciling differences between different <em>darshana</em>-s, or which <em>yajña</em>-s are to be performed when. One can be smug and say they are not required to know any of these because Bhagavān himself that only <em>bhakti</em> in him will emancipate you but then such comments only make it more clear that reading Bhagavadgītā in isolation teaches you nothing about the larger civilization and its important attributes that have been praised by Bhagavān himself at other points.</p>
<p>I would understand if people read the 18 chaptered Bhagavadgītā as a starting point, with the knowledge that there is more to learn and also that it is a part of a much, much larger story. But such is not the case. People read few commentaries on Bhagavadgītā, if at all one properly, claim to understand what <em>karma</em>, <em>jñana</em> and <em>bhakti</em> <em>yoga</em>-s mean then&hellip; do nothing. No one follows <em>varṇāshrama</em> just because they read Bhagavadgītā. You <strong>cannot</strong> claim to have done this if you have not read rest of Mahābhārata or had the guidance of some other <em>vidvān</em> along side. And this is only a case of reading one part of the scripture then going around claiming you understood literally anything. People tend to give the same treatment to other <em>purāṇa</em>-s and <em>smṛti</em>-s. Why would you read the Manusmṛti while never attempting to understand its application or the history it is connected with? There have been 0 recorded cases of oil being poured into a Shūdra&rsquo;s ear for literally any reason, let only hearing <em>vedamantra</em>-s, in the past 3 millennia. This is a huge amount of time if you do not realize. The same Manusmṛti also talks about many more things other than just the position of women and <em>shūdra</em>-s but such things are never the focus. Such divinity is treated only as an imagination of brāhmaṇa-s (of course lmao) and comments on women and <em>shūdra</em>-s are treated as some lived reality.</p>
<p>Each generation is a little different, goes through different circumstances and that can definitely bring about some discord in understanding things that happened about 2000 years ago. But the point here is, we must acknowledge that we do not live in a society of 2000 years ago. We just simply do not have the experience of people who claimed to follow Manusmṛti. Only with such an acknowledgement, only while recognizing that our ancestors were not primitive savages who based their understanding of the world on complete hatred for other groups can you actually claim to understand what the <em>smṛti</em>-s are getting at. To sum this section up, one must read the scriptures in their totality, not isolating certain parts, and then passing judgements without any experience of <em>dharma</em> and <em>dhārmika</em> societies.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>If your entry into <em>dharma</em> has been through the <em>dharmashāstra</em>-s, always remember that <em>dharma</em> is meant to be enacted, not merely theorized and thought of. And you can only achieve this if you have read the said <em>dharmashāstra</em>-s in their totality, and also with the understanding of the proper historical and societal context.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on fourth chapter from Lokamanya Tilak&#39;s Orion</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/009-notes-on-orion-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 09:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/009-notes-on-orion-4/</guid>
      <description>It has been previously discussed how the vernal equinox was in kṛttikā nakṣatra. In the same Taittirīya Saṇhitā mantra, there are also mentions of Phālguna and Caitra paurṇamī-s, which are mentioned as alternate days for ekāṣṭaka, the day samvatsara satra and other year long sacrifices should usually begin. We must side-track to discuss this a little further since in the previous blog it was not all that relevant. Ekāṣṭaka here has been intrepreted to mean, by Mimānsaka-s following Jaimini, and Āpasthamba, as the kṛṣṇa aṣṭamī of Māgha.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It has been <a href="https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/004-notes-on-orion-3/">previously discussed</a> how the vernal equinox was in <em>kṛttikā nakṣatra</em>. In the same <em>Taittirīya Saṇhitā mantra</em>, there are also mentions of <em>Phālguna</em> and <em>Caitra paurṇamī</em>-s, which are mentioned as alternate days for <em>ekāṣṭaka</em>,  the day <em>samvatsara satra</em> and other year long sacrifices should usually begin. We must side-track to discuss this a little further since in the previous blog it was not all that relevant. <em>Ekāṣṭaka</em> here has been intrepreted to mean, by <em>Mimānsaka</em>-s following Jaimini, and Āpasthamba, as the <em>kṛṣṇa aṣṭamī</em> of <em>Māgha</em>. There were some objections to this day, since it is said to be a &lsquo;distressed&rsquo; day, for the following reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>According to the <em>bhāshyakāra</em> Sāyaṇa, it is &lsquo;distressed&rsquo; because the previous year has already ended, and that the preparations for the new <em>satra</em> must commence before the new year commences and not just after the previous year ends</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>According to another <em>bhāshyakāra</em> Shabara, it is &lsquo;distressed&rsquo; because it is extremely cold during this time, and taking holy baths during this time would be undelightful</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Shabara also holds that the word &lsquo;reversed&rsquo; (<em>vyasta</em>) here means reversing of the <em>āyana</em>, meaning the change brought in due to the recent winter solstice</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>These are the objections to <em>ekāṣṭaka</em>, hence the alternatives being provided. Both of these days are mentioned to be &ldquo;mouth of the year&rdquo;. But why should there be <em>three</em> beginnings to an year? Sāyaṇa asserts that because these months fall in first of seasons, <em>vasanta</em>. He also tries to say this can be the case because the days can be interpreted as solar and lunar, but we must remember that the lunar calendar has always been adjusted to match the solar calendar, in our times with the addition of <em>adhika māsa</em>. There is really no basis to fully believe in such double tracking of dates, and hence must be interpreted differently. It may be fair to say that, like currently, as also in Sāyaṇa&rsquo;s times, <em>vasanta</em> began in <em>Phālguna</em> but we have no reason to believe it did the in the same month during the times of <em>shruti</em>-s. There are also other <em>mantra</em>-s in other <em>Brāhmaṇa</em>-s that put <em>Phālguna paurṇamī</em> as the first night of the year, meaning the night of the first day of a new year. So the only logical conclusion here is that the all these three days have been, at different points, the beginnings of the year, that is the winter solstice, and have been remembered in tradition (according to Tilak, they cannot be the vernal equinox because such interpretation would give &lsquo;unreasonable&rsquo; dates). A commentator by the name of Bhāskara Bhaṭṭa explains as much, commenting on the <em>Saṇhita mantra</em>-s:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>एवं दूषयित्वा पक्षान्तरं परिगृण्हाति फल्गुनीपूरर्णमास इत्यादि। फल्गुन्या युक्तः पूर्णमासः फल्गुनीपूर्णमासः। मुखं वा इति। अत्र केचिदा(हृः?) फाल्गुनादि संवत्सर इति।</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So considering that when <em>Phālguna paurṇamī</em> was the first night of the year, winter solstice fell near <em>uttara bhādrapadā</em>, the vernal equinox in <em>mṛgashīra</em>, summer solstice in <em>uttara phalguni</em> and autumnal equinox in <em>mūla</em>. I would like to emphasize that we are talking of the <em>nakṣatra</em>-s here, and that the reader does not correlate them with the <em>māsa</em>-s named after them.  The solstitial and equinoctical events are tracked through the path of the Sun, and only the <em>tithi</em> is lunar. Alright, but this is just a theory based on one interpretation of those <em>mantra</em>-s. So, is there any chance we find support for this in the <em>Veda</em>-s?</p>
<p><em>Āgrahāyaṇi</em>, which literally means &ldquo;commencing the year&rdquo; (also could mean &ldquo;first-coming&rdquo;) is a synonym for <em>mṛgashīra</em>, and hence the month itself being called <em>Āgrahāyaṇika</em> or simply <em>Agrahāyaṇa</em>. In <em>uttarapatha</em> villages of India, <em>Mārgashīra</em> is still called <em>Agahan</em>, clearly stemming from <em>Agrahāyaṇa</em>. If the older understanding of commencing a year from the vernal equinox be applied to this, this means <em>mṛgashīra</em> gets this name because it was quite literally the first <em>nakṣatra</em> of the year. Tilak discusses some derivations and etymology of <em>Āgrahāyaṇi</em>, and he says that it appears in providing such etymology, there was some confusion between <em>Āgrahāyaṇi</em> and <em>Āgrahāyaṇa</em> and the ancient grammarians assumed <em>Āgrahāyaṇa</em> to mean the <strong>month</strong> of <em>Mārgashīra</em> instead of the <strong><em>nakṣatra</em></strong> of <em>mṛgashīra</em>. This discussion is extremely detailed and covers many commentators and different rules of <em>vyākaraṇa</em>, which this idiot writer cannot fully explain and also since these are just notes, are not really worth getting into currently. Basically, the confusion is explained away and we are to understand that, as mentioned earlier,  <em>Āgrahāyaṇa</em> or <em>Agrahāyaṇa</em> is the <em>nakṣatra</em>, and not the month (primarily, the month gets its name due to the former). And just as <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> in <em>Māgha</em> means vernal equinox falling in <em>kṛttikā</em>, <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> in <em>Phālguna</em> means vernal equinox in <em>mṛgashīra</em>. And even more if the autumnal equinox against <em>kṛttikā</em> in <em>vishākhā</em> renders it to mean &ldquo;divided&rdquo; in the equinoctical sense, autumnal equinox against <em>mṛgashīra</em> in <em>mūla</em> would render its meaning as the &ldquo;root&rdquo; (or first) in the sense that it was the first <em>nakṣatra</em> that rose in the east upon the evening. But this meaning of <em>mūla</em> is still conjecture.</p>
<p><em>Uttarāyaṇa</em> on <em>Phālguna paurṇamī</em> puts the start of <em>dakṣiṇāyana</em> on <em>Bhādrapada paurṇamī</em>, in the <em>nakṣatra</em> of <em>uttara phalguna</em>. This makes <em>Bhādrapada kṛṣṇapakṣa</em> as the first <em>pakṣa</em> of <em>dakṣiṇāyana</em>. Those aware of the traditions, will definitely know that the <em>pitṛ pakṣa</em> also begins in <em>Bhādrapada</em> even today. And there is no better reason as to why <em>Bhādrapada kṛṣṇapakṣa</em> should specifically mark this period, apart from the ancient memory of a <em>pitṛ pakṣa</em> beginning at this time. Expanding our horizons here, if we look to other Indo-European cultures, we do find similar traditions and practices. For example, the festival of <em>Fravardigan</em> celebrated among the Pārsi-s is also a festival to celebrate the ancestors of Zoroastrians, which begins around vernal equinox today, Pārsi new year day. But there are grounds to believe that the older-Avestan calendar began not with vernal equinox, but with summer solstice. This is in keeping with how the Zoroastrians are opposed to <em>vaidika</em>-s in many aspects, and if the latter began their year with the colder, darker winter solstice, surely the former would choose the more hotter, dampier summer solstice. More information can be found from <a href="http://www.avesta.org/taqizad.htm">this site</a>. Additionally, the fourth month since <em>Fravardigan</em>, <em>Trishtreye</em> is the month of Sirius constellation, which is close to <em>mṛgashīra</em>, and hence would become the <em>vaidika</em> equivalent of <em>Mārgashīra</em>. Also the fourth month before <em>Fravardigan</em>, <em>Dathusho</em> is dedicated to the Creator, <em>Ahura Mazda</em> which makes sense metaphorically if you consider that in the same time period <em>Dathusho</em> would have begun with the vernal equinox and hence would be the month of plenty. Could such attribution to <em>Ahura Mazda</em> also imply that at one point the Avestan calendar too began with the vernal equinix like the old <em>vaidika</em> calendar? We do not know for sure, but it is not entirely impossible.</p>
<p>We will further see extremely ancient legends attached to these <em>nakṣatra</em>-s spanning different cultures that would further make a case for <em>mṛgashīra</em> stronger. Something to keep in mind is, so far Tilak ji has not commented on <em>Caitra paurṇamī</em>, on whether it was meant as a even older date or something else, because if it is the former the dating of such recordings goes even further back. We shall see if any such clarifications are made in following chapters.</p>
<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Karṇa: Little more than a chelā</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/008-karna-chela/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/008-karna-chela/</guid>
      <description>He was alone. He was helpless. He was denied opportunities. He had everything taken from him. Yet he made his way to the top. Yet he stood by his friends in their times of need. An example of great hardwork. Dāna Vīra Sūrya Putra Karṇa.
What a load of bullshit lmao.
Karṇa is a good representation of selective attention and denial while reading, or more likely the non-reading of Mahābhārata. In modern day narratives, Karṇa has been elevated to the status of a &amp;ldquo;tragic-hero&amp;rdquo;, a prevelant Greek theme that people now look for in the itihāsa-s and purāṇa-s for whatever reason.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>He was alone. He was helpless. He was denied opportunities. He had everything taken from him. Yet he made his way to the top. Yet he stood by his friends in their times of need. An example of great hardwork. Dāna Vīra Sūrya Putra Karṇa.</p>
<p>What a load of bullshit lmao.</p>
<p>Karṇa is a good representation of selective attention and denial while reading, or more likely the <em>non</em>-reading of Mahābhārata. In modern day narratives, Karṇa has been elevated to the status of a &ldquo;tragic-hero&rdquo;, a prevelant Greek theme that people now look for in the <em>itihāsa</em>-s and <em>purāṇa</em>-s for whatever reason. I am not going discuss that psychological condition here, but anyone who has actually read the Mahābhārata, and I should emphasize, <strong>read it in its entirety</strong>, knows that Karṇa was little more than a <em>celā</em> of Duryodhana. One of the primary antagonists for sure, but not a serious threat. Karṇa was mostly relevant because of his birth, his relation to Kuntī and consequently the Pāṇḍava-s, but nothing more than a thorn that can be flung away. But &ldquo;expert&rdquo; opinions from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karna#Dharma-ethics">Wikipedia</a> article on him, which mind you quotes not one traditional thinker, would have you believe otherwise.</p>
<p>Let me assert this: Karṇa is <strong>not</strong> a tragic hero. Karṇa is <strong>not</strong> down trodden. Karṇa is an <em>adharma pātra</em>, a bringer of discord. That unadulterated stupidity on Wikipedia article can be applied better to people like Bhīṣma or Yudhiṣṭhira but <strong>not</strong> Karṇa. We shall see what the Mahābhārata actually says about him.</p>
<p>Let me make something else clear, and <em>I</em> feel stupid that I have to clarify this: <strong>Mahābhārata is the source of Karṇa&rsquo;s story</strong>. You would not know about Karṇa if Mahābhārata did not mention him. You have no other source to peddle your fan-fiction of Karṇa. You will hence accept what the Mahābhārata has to say about him. If the Mahābhārata has been composed by evil, cunning brāhmaṇa-s then they also put in the stories of his &ldquo;struggles&rdquo;. Because I intend to use this phrase a few times in the blog, I am going to label it as &ldquo;<em>niyama</em>&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Now we will take a look at Karṇa and how he is portrayed in the epic. While I am going to rely primarily on the Critical Edition by BORI, I will use regional versions whenever necessary. The <em>kathā</em> of Karṇa&rsquo;s birth is well know so we will not dwell on it too much. He was adopted by a <em>sūta</em> named Adhiratha and his wife, Rādhā (CE/3/15/10). Now, Adhiratha was Dhṛtarāṣṭra&rsquo;s friend. At this point in the story, Dhṛtarāṣṭra is the king of an unrivalled kingdom, mostly due to Bhīṣma. So one should consider the status of Adhiratha and consequently Karṇa himself after adoption while lamenting about Karṇa&rsquo;s childhood. Karṇa is named Vasuṣeṇa by the brāhmaṇa-s and he studied under Droṇa, Kṛpā and Bhārgava Rāma, popularly known as <em>Parshu</em> Rāma. Before we go ahead, that Karṇa studied <em>dhanurvidyā</em> under Droṇa and Kṛpā, along with the other Kaurava-s should readily shatter any narrative that he was denied education because of his <em>jāti</em>. But this is never the point of focus, it is always the one concerning Rāma.</p>
<p>Karṇa wanted to study the <em>daivīya astra</em>-s under Rāma. While the Mahābhārata does not directly mention why, there is an agreement generally that Rāma would not teach any non-brāhmaṇa-s, due to his wrath against the kṣatriya-s. This includes Karṇa, in both the cases of him being a sūta or a kṣatriya. So what do you do when you are not allowed in an educational institute for whatever reason. That&rsquo;s right, you disguise yourself and fool the teacher. And that is exactly what Karṇa does. He disguises himself as a brāhmaṇa and studies under Rāma for some time. This deceit of his is spurred when Indra takes the form an insect, pierces Karṇa on his thighs, and Karṇa being able to bear the pain of the bite, showed Rāma that he was infact not a brāhmaṇa, who curses him for the same reason. And the curse was that he would <em>forget</em> this <em>vidyā</em>. So let this be clear, Karṇa was not cursed for being a sūta, he was cursed for his attempted deception. How is this not justified? The only thing in this story that seems strange to me is how low of a pain tolerance do brāhmaṇa-s have to not be able to bear a small insect bite. But ok, we take those. Nevertheless, Rāma does properly teach Karṇa and even gives him the divine bow Vijaya. It was made by Vishvakarma himself and given to Rāma by Indra (CE/8/1/22). This bow is &ldquo;superior to Gāṇḍīva&rdquo; according to Karṇa himself. So now with all of this in mind, when was Karṇa exactly &ldquo;denied&rdquo; any education?</p>
<p>Do not worry, we shall touch on Rāma not teaching non-brāhmaṇa-s too, if that was indeed the case. This is justified along the same lines as Karṇa &lsquo;deserving&rsquo; anything, it was Rāma&rsquo;s right. Why exactly should he not have a preference when he is imparting extremely divine knowledge? Rāma does not have to teach anyone who he does not want to, much less should one use deception to cross boundaries set by Rāma for himself. Rāma did teach Bhīṣma, but he is exceptional in pretty much every category. In fact, not everyone is worthy of learning the divine <em>astra</em>-s anyway. Droṇa initially refused to give his own son Ashvatthāmā the <em>brahmashīrāstra</em> (CE/10/2/3) and let Arjuna learn it before him. If you want knowledge, you do it the right way. When an <em>ācārya</em> refuses to teach something or someone, you respect that and move on, not brute force yourself against their wishes. Whatever Karṇa suffered here is hundred-percent justified. No casteism, no discrimination. Only the <em>phala</em> of his <em>karma</em>-s.</p>
<p>Let us dwell on the kind of person Karṇa was, and whether he is a &ldquo;tragic-hero&rdquo; in any capacity. Now tragic hero as an idea, mainly highlighted in Greek works, though conceptually can be found in literature around the world, is a character or a person who makes morally ambiguous, if not outright repulsive choices, for the &ldquo;greater good&rdquo;. Exceptions exist to everything and a &ldquo;tragedy&rdquo; and &ldquo;hero&rdquo; might have differing meanings in the context of a story itself, regardless the point is Karṇa is shown to be a victim of the circumstances and that he was still righteous, hence a tragic hero.</p>
<p>Ok, &ldquo;victim of the circumstances&rdquo;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>सन्धाय धार्तराष्ट्रेण पार्थानां विप्रिये स्थितः। योद्धुमाशंसते नित्यं फल्गुनेन महात्मना॥ (CE/3/15/10)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>धृतराष्ट्रस्य तद्वाक्यं निशम्य सहसौबलः। दुर्योधनमिदं काले कर्णो वचनमब्रवीत्॥ (CE/3/11/2)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ये स्म ते नाद्रियन्तेऽऽज्ञा नोद्विजन्ते कदा च न। पश्यामस्ताञ्श्रिया हीनान्पाण्डवान्वनवासिनः॥ श्रूयन्ते हि महाराज सरो द्वैतवनं प्रति। वसन्तः पाण्डवाः सार्धं ब्राह्मणैर्वनवासिभिः॥ स प्रयाहि महाराज श्रिया परमया युतः। प्रतपन्पाण्डुपुत्रांस्त्वं रश्मिवानिव तेजसा॥ स्थितो राज्ये च्युतान्राज्याच्छ्रिया हीनाञ्श्रिया वृतः। असमृद्धान्समृद्धार्थः पश्य पाण्डुसुतान्नृप॥ महाभिजनसम्पन्नं भद्रे महति संस्थितम्। पाण्डवास्त्वाभिवीक्षन्तां ययातिमिव नाहुषम्॥</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>मद्विधस्यायशस्यं हि न युक्तं प्राणरक्षणम्। युक्तं हि यशसा युक्तं मरणं लोकसंमतम्॥ सोऽहमिन्द्राय दास्यामि कुण्डले सह वर्मणा। यदि मां बलवृत्रघ्नो भिक्षार्थमुपयास्यति॥ (CE/3/15/1)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let me give you a gist of these <em>shloka</em>-s, and you can verify them using the various translations that are available online. In the first <em>shloka</em>, Karṇa is explicitly said to have allied (<em>sandhāya</em>) with the sons of Dhṛtarāṣṭra and that he always wanted to rival Arjuna. In the second set of <em>shloka</em>-s, Dhṛtarāṣṭra laments the condition of Pāṇḍava-s when they are residing in the forest and Karṇa, along with Shakuni, &ldquo;advises&rdquo; Duryodhana that they must go to them and show-off Duryodhana&rsquo;s wealth and prosperity. In the third <em>shloka</em>, Karṇa is boasting to Sūrya, who has come to warn him about Indra, that how him donating his <em>kuṇḍala</em>-s and <em>kavaca</em>, even at the detriment of his powers, would bring him fame. So, considering these with some other <em>shloka</em>-s in Ādi Parva which tell how Duryodhana, Karṇa and Shakuni tried to kill Bhīma, how do you make a case for him being the &ldquo;victim&rdquo; of any &ldquo;circumstance&rdquo; here? He is the one creating the circumstances. He is doing this on his own. No one is forcing him into this stupidity. If these are the result of <em>niyama</em> then again remember that very <em>niyama</em> tells Karṇa was abandoned and this and that. The only tragedy here is the incurable idiocy of illiterates who misintepret such explicit <em>shloka</em>-s.</p>
<p>While these should suffice to depict that Karṇa was selfish, there are two more instances that solidfy that aspect of this personality: He has disrupted <strong>two</strong> <em>svayamvara</em>-s. One is of course the Draupadī <em>svayamvara</em> and other is one organized by the king of Kaliṅga named Citrāṇgada (CE/12/1/4). Another instance, which is ironically used to show the &ldquo;complexity&rdquo; of Karṇa, is when he calls Draupadī courtesean (CE/2/8/19). It is mind numbing that people use this just to say that this adds some &ldquo;complexity&rdquo; to Karṇa rather than pairing it with his other attempts to humiliate and kill the Pāṇḍava-s and demonstrate his hatred for the latter. This is exactly what I called it earlier, selective attention. In the larger picture, all the &ldquo;complex&rdquo; actions that Karṇa takes are motivated purely by his hatred of Pāṇḍava-s and Arjuna specifically.</p>
<p>Speaking of <em>svayamvara</em>-s and his rivalry with Arjuna, why do we not take a look at how good a <em>ratha</em> our golden boy was? Indeed, learning from Droṇa, Kṛpā and Bhārgava Rāma should make him one of the greatest <em>ratha</em>-s of his time. These are the following major mentions of Karṇa fighting:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Karṇa&rsquo;s entrance in the main story is quite grand and is filled with literally everything that is popularly peddled in his name. He makes is way among the royal Kuru-s, challenges Arjuna, is questioned by Kṛpā about his birth, upon being unaswerable is made a king by Duryodhana to honor their friendship, gets called out on his <em>jāti</em> by Bhīma, is defended by Duryodhana all the same. But do not let &ldquo;first impression is the best impression&rdquo; get the better of you this time, this is just the beginning of Mahābhārata. (CE/1/8/3)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Next we see him fight during Draupadī <em>svayamvara</em> against Arjuna (CE/1/12/8). Let us address this &ldquo;controversy&rdquo; of Draupadī turning Karṇa away because of him being a sūta. Yes, in some versions of Mahābhārata, this indeed happens. This is completely justified in a <em>varṇāshrama</em> based society, but I do not think any such justification of it being a <em>svayamvara</em>, Draupadī&rsquo;s choice yada yada matters in any way. So now I ask you, why exactly should we use this specific version of Mahābhārata to begin with? Because in the Kumbakonam version, Karṇa does actually participate and fails to string the bow by a hair&rsquo;s margin <a href="https://sanskritdocuments.org/mirrors/mahabharata/mbhK/mahabharata-k-01-sa.html">(KK/1/202)</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ततो वैकर्तनः कर्णो वृषा वै सूतनन्दनः। धनुरभ्याशमागम्य तोलयामास तद्धनुः॥ तं चाप्यारोप्यमाणं तद्रोममात्रेऽभ्यताडयत्। त्रैलोक्यविजयी कर्णः सत्वे त्रैलोक्यविश्रुतः॥</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ok, you have one versions saying he was subjected to &ldquo;casteism&rdquo; and other saying he failed to do it. So tell me, on which grounds would you take the word of the former to the word of latter? For instance, I can discard the manuscripts that say Karṇa was not allowed to participate and use only Kumbakonam and my arguments will stand entirely. <em>Arthāt</em>, I can easily switch between versions without any holes in my assertions but clearly those who prefer the non-participation version of the <em>kathā</em> do not have any solid justifications for their preference. It is not even clear if these people realize there are two versions of the story to begin with. We&rsquo;ll talk about Draupadī&rsquo;s &ldquo;casteism&rdquo; when people who only talk of this version explain theirs.</p>
<p>Anyway, when Arjuna wins Draupadī, other kings are pissed and they start rampaging. Arjuna and Karṇa face-off. Guess who wins? Well, it is more of a stalemate, but can be considered a victory for Arjuna still. You see, in their current conditions, Arjuna and Karṇa could not have been more apart. Arjuna was on the run along with his brothers and mother because Duryodhana had just a few weeks ago tried to burn them alive and were living in secrecy, roaming village to village, in simple cotton clothes. Arjuna did not even have his Gāṇḍīva yet (he would only get it after a dozen or more years since now). On the other hand, Karṇa arrived with the Kaurava-s, as the king of Aṅga, with his own retinue, this golden <em>kavaca</em> still on him and the rampaging kings supporting him. He presumably also had his bow, Vijaya, which is mentioned earlier. Karṇa has no reason or disadvantage to <em>not win</em> this outright. Yet Arjuna with all his disadvantages manages to fend off Karṇa.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>His third mentioned battle is during the Pāṇḍava <em>digvijaya</em> against Bhīma himself. He loses and is subjugated (CE/2/5/3).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>His fourth endeavor is against the Gandharva-s, when he advised Duryodhana to show-off his wealth to the miserable Pāṇḍava-s mentioned earlier (CE/3/11/9-10). He runs away from the overwhelming force of Gandharva-s and returns after quite a while, probably when he thinks the situation has cooled off.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>He helps in the seige of Matsya, after Bhīma kills Kīcaka, resulting in Kaurava-s and Trigarta-s attacking the now commander-less kingdom. He is the first to attack Arjuna among the Kurushreṣṭha-s along with some tributary kings and loses immediately (CE/4/3/26).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>He, along with Duryodhana, tries to tie down the creator of everything <em>vyakta</em> and <em>avyakta</em>, Vāsudeva Kṛṣṇa, only to get <em>vishvarūpa</em>&rsquo;d (CE/5/6/58-59).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>He fights in the Kurukṣetra war from the eleventh day, after Bhīṣma falls. There are many, many battles that all the <em>ratha</em>-s engage in and it is unecessary to list them all, so I will mention the important ones:</p>
<ul>
<li>On the thirteenth day, he took part in the subjugation of Abhimanyu, cutting his bow down (CE/7/3/16)</li>
<li>On the fourteenth day, a long battle took place between Bhīma and Karṇa (CE/7/5, the exact chapter numbers can not be provided because the battle lasts for the entire <em>upaparva</em>). Initially Bhīma fends off Karṇa, primarily because the target for the day was Jayadrata, but Karṇa comes back and they continue their fight. Each time Karṇa is at a disadvantage, Duryodhana sends more and more waves of tributary kings to help him against an unconquerable Bhīma. But Bhīma&rsquo;s ceiling is pushed to its maximum and he falls. Karṇa does not kill him because of the promise he makes to Kuntī earlier.</li>
<li>As fourteenth day of war continues into the night, Karṇa is forced to use the <em>shakti astra</em> he gets from Indra after he gives up his <em>kavaca</em> on Ghaṭotkaca.</li>
<li>Karṇa is made the <em>senāpati</em> on the sixteenth day. He proceeds to wreck havoc on the Pāṇḍava armies.</li>
<li>On the seventeenth day, he fights Arjuna for the first and the last time in Kurukṣetra and is killed.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>As should be clear from these mentions, Karṇa was never on the same level as Arjuna, and would lose to <em>ratha</em>-s who are equal to the latter or maybe even lesser. He was indeed a strong warrior in general, but the differnce between his and his rival&rsquo;s strength was night and day. Arjuna never lost to anyone in any of his battles, except against Mahādeva himself. Bhīma has a similar record, but his defeat at the hand of Karṇa in Kurukṣetra is the result of nothing but the smaller Pāṇḍava armies focusing all their strength on killing Jayadrata and the larger Kaurava armies focusing on defending him at any cost. Bhīṣma&rsquo;s worst result was a stalemate against his <em>guru</em> Bhārgava Rāma and in his encounters against Arjuna, he held back and never tried to cause actual damage to any of the Pāṇḍava-s, only the allied Pāṇḍava armies. There are smaller incidents here and there but this list should suffice for now. If these are also results of <em>niyama</em>, then why mention Karṇa having any strength at all?</p>
<p>Finally, let us discuss his celebrated &ldquo;friendship&rdquo; with Duryodhana. For completely deranged reasons, Duryodhana and Karṇa are icons of great friends but not Kṛṣṇa and Arjuna. Karṇa&rsquo;s loyalty to Duryodhana is the same as a gambler&rsquo;s &ldquo;loyalty&rdquo; to poker and an alcoholic&rsquo;s &ldquo;loyalty&rdquo; to drinks. It was destructive and should not be celebrated. Karṇa was the one actively encouraging Duryodhana to pick fights with Pāṇḍava-s and this has been brought up multiple times in this blog. There is no doubt that he was indeed loyal to Duryodhana and his family, but in the wake of a destructive war it is entirely misplaced. Additionally, some of these qualities of (misplaced) loyalty along with the &ldquo;donating to brāhmaṇa-s&rdquo; and the giving away of his <em>kavaca</em> to Indra are at the forefront of Karṇa praise. But I would seriously doubt an individual&rsquo;s mental capabilities if considering the entirety of this blog they somehow think these few attributes bring any balance to Karṇa&rsquo;s morality. They do not. Karṇa is still 7 parts <em>adhārmika</em> if he is 3 parts <em>dhārmika</em> at all.</p>
<p>Ultimately, his speech in <em>Karṇa Upanivāda Parva</em> in response to Kṛṣṇa&rsquo;s attemp to convince him to join Pāṇḍava-s is very sober and mature. He is concious of the choices he has made and he is at peace with his identity. He never cries that life or anyone treated him unfairly. He in fact regrets &ldquo;the harsh words [he] used against the Pāṇḍava-s to please Dhṛtarāṣṭra’s son&rdquo; (CE/5/7/2), admitting his faults entirely. Reading this speech, one cannot help but make way for some respect for the golden boy. But <em>this</em> complexity is never discussed. It is everything around it, unfortunately.</p>
<p>This blog is too large already for me to cover other, smaller discussions. Completely fictious depictions of Karṇa have become part of the pop-culture, like in the movie <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raajneeti">Raajneeti</a> or the award winning poem by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shivaji_Sawant">Shivaji Sawant</a>, Mrutyunjay and other plethora of such works. It is exhausting to even try and watch/read these because of how blatantly false they are. So on an ending note, Karṇa is not a person worthy of any praise. Any <em>dhārmika</em> act he does, is not only cancelled out by his other deplorable acts, but they are too small when compared to other people from his times. It is in fact not Karṇa who is pitiable here, is it his brothers the Pāṇḍava-s. I hope people respect the Mahābhārata and read it properly, and see the things and people as they are.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Āryīkaraṇa of Writing: Some Proposals</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/007-aryikarana-of-writing-dvi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 10:09:45 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/007-aryikarana-of-writing-dvi/</guid>
      <description>In part 1 of this topic, I discussed some preliminary obstacles in the way of āryīkaraṇa. No doubt there would be more complexities going forward but we can tackle these for now.
I will now present some ideas have I in my attempts to make writing material covenient and simpler in Sanskrit. And I would like to emphasis on convenient here, because for the reasons I discussed earlier, it makes no sense to try and shift the system wholesale into Sanskrit.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/006-aryikarana-of-writing/">part 1</a> of this topic, I discussed some preliminary obstacles in the way of <em>āryīkaraṇa</em>. No doubt there would be more complexities going forward but we can tackle these for now.</p>
<p>I will now present some ideas have I in my attempts to make writing material covenient and simpler in Sanskrit. And I would like to emphasis on <em>convenient</em> here, because for the reasons I discussed earlier, it makes no sense to try and shift the system wholesale into Sanskrit. Instead of being productive, it is simply going to dissuade people away from any such attempts. So let me start with something extremely simple: writing dates.</p>
<p>Any practicing Hindu uses two calendars, the Gregorian for all the civil considerations and the <em>pancāṅga</em>-s for all <em>dhārmika</em> tasks. There should be an attempt, however small-scale, to write <em>tithī</em>-s whenever possible either instead of or along with the Gregorian dates. Gregorian date formats are various but standardized: <em>dd/mm/yyyy</em>, <em>dd-mm-yy</em>, <em>mm/dd/yy</em>, etc., and there is also the timezone difference but whatever be the diversities it is a standard and you can very easily understand any format and also convert the timezones if you know the hour-differential. Keeping convenience in mind, here is what I propose:</p>





<pre tabindex="0"><code>tithī (pakṣa number) - māsa (initial of the first pakṣa) - samvatsara

14(1) - 09 (कृ) - 2080
14(2) - 08 (शु) - 2080</code></pre><p>&hellip;which reads like &ldquo;<em>mārgashīrsha kṛṣṇapakṣa caturdashī</em>&rdquo; or &ldquo;<em>kārttikā kṛṣṇapakṣa caturdashī</em>&rdquo; of 2080 <em>vikrama samvatsara</em>. The <em>pakṣa</em> number will be relative to the <em>pakṣa</em> the month starts from, <em>arthāt</em> the <em>pancāṅga</em>-s that follow <em>pūrṇimā tithī</em> would have <em>shuklapakṣa</em> as 1 and <em>amāvāsyā tithī</em> as 2 and vice versa. To make it clear which is which, the initial of the starting <em>pakṣa</em> can be written adjacent to the <em>māsa</em> number. So, <code>09(कृ)</code> denotes that the month of <em>mārgashīsha</em> in the <em>pancāṅga</em> followed here begins with <em>kṛṣṇapakṣa</em>. Adjustments can be made accordingly for other formats. In this way, the difference between <em>pancāṅga</em>-s can be accounted for. We have a flexibility in this case, but it must be understood that there will be some loss of diveristy when we commit to standardization. It will not be without a cause of course. There must exist an understanding of the principle of representation, rather than the content itself. Without such understanding among the implementers, all of this is amounts to <em>shūnya</em>.</p>
<p>While this is my recommendation, I would encourage for more intuitive ways to use <em>tithī</em>-s for civil matters, if such a way exists. Something else to consider is how would we represent a day when two <em>tithī</em>-s fall on the same day, because <em>tithī</em>-s are lunar and we are accustomed to follow calendars built on solar calculations. So, is using <em>tithī</em>-s even a good idea? These things can only be judged when lots of people implement them for trial and error.</p>
<p>Let us consider a more complex case now: representation of Mathematical problems. This is a subject our ancestors excelled at. And they wrote out all the problems, instead of using notations like we do today. Probably some variables could have been used, but nothing close to modern day notations such as <code>∑</code>,<code>∫</code>,<code>∴</code>, etc. And these symbols are largely just Greek or Latin letters. And usage of these scripts is understandable given the regions where modern Mathematics developed. We can put off the discussion for noting a method like summation or integration for now and focus on just the variables, to make a quick point.</p>
<p>Typically, Latin letters like a, b, p, q, x, y or Greek letters like α, β, γ, δ and others are used as required in different problems and methods. We can very well use devanāgarī script and use the letters क, ख, ग <em>ityādi</em> but there are couple of considerations here. Devanāgarī letters are a little more complicated to make than Greeco-Latin, and especially Latin. Not only that, since pairs of letters like (a, b), (x, y) are chosen because they are consecutive in the alphabet list and not arbitrarily, it only makes sense to use consecutives like (क, ख), (ग, घ) in our attempts too, but this puts strain on the pronunciation a little to properly differentiate the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aspirated_consonant"><em>sparsha</em> sounds</a> from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenuis_consonant"><em>mahāprāṇa</em></a>. I support this, since <em>shikṣā</em> is a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vedanga"><em>vedāṅga</em></a>. But I can understand if people would like to use more spaced out sounds like क, च, ग so there is no lapse in pronunciation at all. That being said, just as European scholars used Greek as a &ldquo;dead&rdquo; script to represent some of their variables, we too can use the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brahmi_script">Brāhmī script</a>. Every major Indian script derives in some way from Brāhmī, but Brāhmī itself has not been in use for over a millenium. This is not an attempt to &ldquo;revive&rdquo; the script, merely use its characters like Greek characters are used.</p>
<p>Some characters like 𑀓(क), 𑀚(ज), 𑀢(ट) might need to be avoided until Brāhmī is standardized, since these can cause confusion against the more popular notations of similar designs. That being said, let us try and see how this can work in action:</p>





<pre tabindex="0"><code>f(𑀯) = 𑁫𑀯 ‍+ 𑁩

सततगणन 𑀯 
एतस्य क्रिया f(𑀯) श्रेणौ [𑀲𑀸, 𑀦𑀺]

अधुना वयम् एतत् 𑀯 अङ्काः गति इच्छयते प्रति 𑀲 क्षणेषु

एतत् क्रिया F(𑀯) उपयोगतः दर्शय शक्नोसि

अत्र F(𑀯) f(𑀯) क्रियायाः समुच्च्य 𑀯 अङ्केषु

ततः

 𑀯𑀺F(𑀯) 
——————— [𑀯 = 𑀲𑀸...𑀯] = f(𑀯)
  𑀯𑀺𑀯

एतत् अन्तरगणितस्य मूल प्रमेयस्य प्रथम भागः</code></pre><p>The above snippet, is an attempt to depict the First Part of the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus in Sanskirt, however amateur,  with Brāhmī characters in use. The notation of <code>f()</code> to represent a function is retained so that some of it is recognizable. Here, <code>𑀯</code> is a variable, literally <em>vikārī</em> and is represented by the Brāhmī character of the same sound <em>va</em>. The range <code>[𑀲𑀸, 𑀦𑀺]</code> reads <em>[sā, ni]</em>, which are just the first and last <em>svara</em>-s from Indian musical notes (because that too is a &ldquo;range&rdquo;, and I needed something more concrete to represent rather than just consecutive letters or other technicalities discussed before). <code>𑀯𑀺</code> reads <em>vi</em> for <em>vibheda</em>, modern word for differentiation, to represent <code>dy/dx</code> notation.</p>
<p>It is not clean, maybe even awkward to read and harder to understand, but you would not recognize it if it was written out in Russian, Chinese or Japanese either (assuming people reading this are not familiar with these languages). It is not because you simply do not know how to interpret this, you are also not used to reading complicated material in Sanskrit. But there is no other alternative but to keep pushing for these until better people over a period of time can make such representations cleaner and people get used to it. This is going to be a generational effort, with everyone understanding that some writing habits must be conceded and some must be adopted.</p>
<p>These are some proposals of mine. They are basic and meant to get the point across. I will endeavor to try and implement somethings in Chemistry too, considering the vast system of naming conventions followed in Organic Chemistry would work very well with Sanskrit. But that is one for the future.</p>
<p>The strength of Sanskrit, however beautifully depicted in poetry, must not be isolated to it. It was used at one point for everything in the high culture, and me hopes that <em>ārya</em>-s will use it again one day, churning its vast capabilities.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Āryīkaraṇa of Writing: Preliminary Obstacles</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/006-aryikarana-of-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 10:10:41 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/006-aryikarana-of-writing/</guid>
      <description>A mark of powerful civilizations is the integrative, or more historically, the dominating force they exert on other, small civilizations and communities. The ongoing incorporation of western-liberal thought, born in Christian colonization of the past few centuries, just represents the success of Christian supremacists, irrespective of one&amp;rsquo;s likeness to this. The fact that we write in English, use idioms and phrases and formal systems developed during this era is very well discussed and accepted unanimously, with minimal opposition.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A mark of powerful civilizations is the integrative, or more historically, the dominating force they exert on other, small civilizations and communities. The ongoing incorporation of western-liberal thought, born in Christian colonization of the past few centuries, just represents the success of Christian supremacists, irrespective of one&rsquo;s likeness to this. The fact that we write in English, use idioms and phrases and formal systems developed during this era is very well discussed and accepted unanimously, with minimal opposition. In fact, quite laughably, any critique and opposition against the hegemony of English is also <em>written in English</em>, for universal consumption.</p>
<p>There are people who do endeavor to write and represent subjects and sciences in local scripts and languages whenever possible. This attempt might seem futile to majority of the aforementioned public who have accepted English as <em>lingua franca</em> unopposed, but countries like Japan, China, Germany, etc., do require, if not mandate, learning of their regional languages in order for communication and business. And these countries are successful at that. It is ironic to me that now and again I see some individuals who see merit in English&rsquo;s hegemony claimimg that Sanskrit is the &ldquo;oppressor&rsquo;s language&rdquo; but, are happy to learn German if they want jobs overseas, or that those who enjoy anime, and then develop an urge to learn Japanese, engage in writing <em>hāiku</em>-s.</p>
<p>It is not sufficient that we merely have the will to represent subjects and sciences, complex or simple, in Sanskrit, because it indeed is a powerful language, rather we commit to realizing this will. But let us consider some obstacles before discussing solutions.</p>
<p>Firstly, it must be understood that writing in Sanskrit does not end with just translating whatever you would have written in English otherwise. To illustrate what I mean, take this introductory paragraph from <a href="https://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/bs4/doc/">Beautiful Soup Documentation</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Beautiful Soup is a Python library for pulling data out of HTML and XML files. It works with your favorite parser to provide idiomatic ways of navigating, searching, and modifying the parse tree. It commonly saves programmers hours or days of work.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now this might seem gibberish to a person not familiar with Python or programming in general, but it is equally gibberish to me if I want to write something about Beautiful Soup in Sanskrit. Why? For starters the word &ldquo;library&rdquo; used to describe Beautiful Soup has a very specific meaning in programming, and definitely does not denote the more popular &lsquo;collection of books&rsquo; in this context. So I cannot use the word पुस्तकालय (<em>pustakālaya</em>) when attempting such a task. Taking the second sentence, &ldquo;parser&rdquo;, &ldquo;idiomatic ways of navigating&rdquo;, &ldquo;parse tree&rdquo; &ndash; <strong>all</strong> of these phrases have a very specific meaning and it is not merely enough to translate these into Sanskrit because what you would be doing is just that - translating. You would not be building a culture of writing in Sanskrit relative to these subjects but rather just doing what Google Translate can do. No, the resolve should be to represent very subject of Computer Sciences in Sanskrit in its entirety, so that people who come after you, and whatever progress they make in this field, can also write in Sanskrit, without having second thoughts or feeling awkward.</p>
<p>I just provided a basic example using that site. This is even more true when you get to subjects like Chemistry, Biology, Quantum Physics, etc., because the formal systems of these subjects have developed in Latin/Greek languages and scripts for centuries at this point. While there are Sanskrit works that do deal with, or at least can be interpreted in a way to deal with these, they have not progressed for the same period of time and are stuck when they were being last studied. Those Latin or Greek words, whatever they would have meant originally, come to mean something else entirely. For example, the word &ldquo;calculus&rdquo; in Latin means &ldquo;small rocks&rdquo; or &ldquo;pebbles&rdquo; and became a general word for counting since Roman-s used these pebbles in their counting tools and <em>over-time</em>, much after Roman Empire&rsquo;s collapse, has come to represent a branch of Mathematics that deals with changing of values over a period of some other values. Talk about a rollercoaster. And yes, some of the names of the subjects in Sanskrit are also named after the tools they were used to study such as <em>bīja gaṇita</em> for Algebra or <em>rekhā gaṇita</em> for Geometry, but what I mean is <em>currently</em> we would be trying to come up with words in Sanskrit against Latin words which have developed for centuries. So direct translations too are either insufficient or unnecessary.</p>
<p>And that is exactly what is the issue is here, the time complexity; we are going to be playing catch up for some time, before we can have individuals who think and write, <em><strong>primarily</strong></em> in Sanskrit. I am not going to discuss how can that be achieved because it is obvious: pump up education in Sanskrit. That is really it. And again, it is not sufficient that students score good marks in the subject, there is a necessity of an active culture.</p>
<p>Now, &ldquo;Why?&rdquo; is a good question. What good does it do to convert everything into Sanskrit instead of continuing to use Latin/English. The answers to these are also obvious. We are a Sanskrit people, not English. Many of our ideas can be represented properly only in Sanskrit or its derivatives, not English. Our core tenets like <em>dharma</em>, <em>artha</em>, <em>kāma</em>, <em>mokṣa</em> and other <em>darshana</em>-s can only be understood and practiced if one knows their true meanings only in Sanskrit, not English. But ultimately, there is no better reason or no more a logical reason than we just want Sanskrit to become India&rsquo;s <em>prathama bhāṣā</em> again, since this is one of major features that united us. Hence, &ldquo;<em>āryīkaraṇa</em>&rdquo; of writing, an attempt to shift or define formal systems in Sanskrit, language of <em>ārya</em>-s and its culture.</p>
<p>I will be discussing some solutions and standards we can use for various formal systems in <a href="https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/007-aryikarana-of-writing-dvi/">part 2</a> of this blog.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Blessing and Gratefulness in Rāmāyaṇa</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/005-ramayana-blessing-gratefulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 11:51:36 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/005-ramayana-blessing-gratefulness/</guid>
      <description>That the shāstra-s continuously refer to events that transpired before them is a well-known attribute. Protagonists of a story will be refered to as &amp;ldquo;narendra&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;rājendra&amp;rdquo;, etc., other such epithets which invoke Indra as a superlative, him being the king of deva-s.
There are smaller such incidents, which are just presented as off-handed comments, but are extremely deep and have entire histories attached to them. One such instance is when Rāma is about to leave for the forest, to being his vanavāsa, his grief-stricken mother, Kausalyā pronounces many blessings on him.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>That the <em>shāstra</em>-s continuously refer to events that transpired before them is a well-known attribute. Protagonists of a story will be refered to as &ldquo;<em>narendra</em>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<em>rājendra</em>&rdquo;, etc., other such epithets which invoke Indra as a superlative, him being the king of <em>deva</em>-s.</p>
<p>There are smaller such incidents, which are just presented as off-handed comments, but are extremely deep and have entire histories attached to them. One such instance is when Rāma is about to leave for the forest, to being his <em>vanavāsa</em>, his grief-stricken mother, Kausalyā pronounces many blessings on him. She says, amongst other things:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>यन्मङ्गलं सहस्राक्षे सर्वदेवनमस्कृते। वृत्रनाशे समभवत्तत्ते भवतु मङ्गलम्॥</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>यन्मङ्गलं सुपर्णस्य विनताकल्पयत्पुरा। अमृतं प्रार्थयानस्य तत्ते भवतु मङ्गलम्॥</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Roughly translated as : &ldquo;Which ever auspicious portents occured to the thousand-eyed one when he destroyed Vṛtra, may those occur to you as well. Whatever auspiciouness Vinatā prayed for Suparṇa when he endeavored for <em>amṛta</em>, may those auspicious protents happen to you as well.&rdquo; While Indra&rsquo;s destruction of Vṛtra is among the greatest of <em>ārya</em> stories, acquiring new meanings and forms over long periods of time, Vinatā&rsquo;s story is comparable to Kausalyā&rsquo;s helplessness and they both share a concern for their son, endeavoring on a perilous journey.</p>
<p>Vinatā and Kadrū were the wives of Kashyapa, and the former is the mother of Garuḍa and Aruṇa, while the latter is the mother of all <em>sarpa</em>-s and <em>nāga</em>-s. Vinatā and Kadrū placed a bet, on whether Uccaishravā&rsquo;s tail is black or white. Vinatā said it to be white and Kadrū said it to be black. Considering Uccaishravā is a white horse, naturally all of his parts would also be white. So a case can be made that Kadrū does not know her current affairs. Irregardless, they put on this wager, went over to check on the all-white-horse-with-nothing-black-on-him and Kadrū cheated by asking her sons, the snakes to cover Uccaishravā&rsquo;s tail, which made it appear black in color, thus &ldquo;defeating&rdquo; Vinatā. The condition was whoever was wrong in her guess, would become the slave of the other. Hence Vinatā was now Kadrū&rsquo;s slave.</p>
<p>Kadrū and her sons began to order Vinatā and Garuḍa around accordingly. Needless to say that the latter pair was dejected and after a few adventures of unreasonable requests, Garuḍa asks his half-brothers what would it take to be freed from this slavery. The <em>sarpa</em>-s replied that if Garuḍa bring to them the <em>amṛta</em> of the <em>deva</em>-s from <em>svarga</em>, he and his mother would be free. Garuḍa relayed the same to his mother who pronounced the following blessings unto him:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>पक्षौ ते मारुतः पातु चन्द्रः पृष्ठं तु पुत्रक। शिरस्तु पातु ते वह्निर्भास्करः सर्वमेव तु॥</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Meaning: &ldquo;Let the Maruts protect your wings. O son! Let the moon protect your back. Let the fire protect your head. Let the sun protect all your body.&rdquo; And also that she would always pray to bring him welfare. Saying that these prayers &ldquo;worked&rdquo; is an understatement. Both Garuḍa and Rāma would bring nothing but destruction to their enemies after their endeavors. Garuḍa also became the <em>vāhana</em> of Viṣṇu.</p>
<p>In another instance, <em>pravacanakāra</em>-s to justify Rāma&rsquo;s quality of being &ldquo;<em>kṛtajña</em>&rdquo; (Rāmāyaṇa 1.1.2) cite a story from Bhāgavata Purāṇa. In the 6th <em>adhyāya</em> of 9th <em>skandha</em>, the Ikṣvāku <em>vansha</em> is described. One king of this lineage is Puraṅjaya. The <em>devatā</em>-s and <em>dānava</em>-s were at it again, you know the usual, and they request help from Puraṅjaya. The latter agreed on the condition that Indra would become his <em>vāhana</em>. Indra obviously refuses at first but the at behest Viṣṇu agrees. Indra takes the form of a bull, and Puraṅjaya sits on his back, <em>kukud</em>. They won their fight against the <em>dānava</em>-s and since Puraṅjaya had sat on the back of Indra, he came to be known as Kakutstha, meaning &lsquo;stationed on back&rsquo;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>पुरंजयस्तस्य सुत इन्द्रवाह इतीरितः। ककुत्स्थ इति चाप्युक्तः शृणु नामानि कर्मभिः॥</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Since Rāma descends from Puraṅjaya, he is called &ldquo;<em>Kākutstha</em>&rdquo;, much like how he is called &ldquo;Dāsharathi&rdquo; and &ldquo;Rāghava&rdquo;, thus expressing gratitute to Indra and his ancestor.</p>
<p>These are small things, but a little curiosity goes a long way.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on third chapter from Lokamanya Tilak&#39;s Orion</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/004-notes-on-orion-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 06:02:51 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/004-notes-on-orion-3/</guid>
      <description>Continuing from notes from the first two chapters, though very early on vaidika-s did start their year at the vernal equinox, the tradition shifted to starting the new year at the winter solstice, or what uttarāyaṇa has been representing in our times so far. When and why this happened, we do not know. What I can postulate is that when vaidika-s would&amp;rsquo;ve realized that entire seasons were changing after hundreds of years during the equinoxes, that is to say, the vernal equinox which took place in an asterism that marked the beginning of spring, but now this asterism falls in winter, they would have gone for something more perceptible like the motion of the Sun in the sky, to create a celestial marker for their rituals.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Continuing from <a href="https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/003-notes-on-orion-two-chaps/">notes from the first two chapters</a>, though very early on <em>vaidika</em>-s did start their year at the vernal equinox, the tradition shifted to starting the new year at the winter solstice, or what <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> has been representing in our times so far. When and why this happened, we do not know. What I can postulate is that when <em>vaidika</em>-s would&rsquo;ve realized that entire seasons were changing after hundreds of years during the equinoxes, that is to say, the vernal equinox which took place in an asterism that marked the beginning of spring, but now this asterism falls in winter, they would have gone for something more perceptible like the motion of the Sun in the sky, to create a celestial marker for their rituals. However, I have not come across any scholarly thought to support this.</p>
<p>The point remains, the <em>ārambhaṇīya</em> of the <em>samvatsara satra</em> changed from the day of vernal equinox to winter solstice. Currently, the vernal equinox passes through <em>revatī</em>, but has receded by several degrees. Even still, the vernal equinox falls around 23rd September, in <em>Bhādrapada</em>. This puts the winter solstice, and the beginning of <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> roughly in <em>mṛgashīrṣā</em>, consequently in month of <em>Mārgashīrṣa</em>. However the <em>uttarāyaṇa</em>, in conjuction with <em>makara saṅkrānti</em> is celebrated in the month of <em>Pauṣa</em>. Following articles by <a href="https://koenraadelst.blogspot.com/2020/12/the-real-uttarayana.html">Koenraad Elst</a> and <a href="https://pragyata.com/when-should-pongal-makar-samkranti-be-celebrated-and-why/">A K Kaul</a> go in to details and discussions on this subject. Whatever be the tradition of dates, the tradition of principle dictates we consider <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> to fall in <em>Mārgashīrṣa</em>. However, considering the antiquity of <em>shāstra</em>-s, there would have been a time when the equinox and solstice fell later than it does, and ritual timings would have followed these markers. This is indeed the case.</p>
<p>Firstly, there are grounds to believe that <em>kṛttikā</em>, and NOT <em>ashvinī</em>, was the first in the list of <em>nakṣatra</em>-s. The <em>mantra</em>-s from <em>Taittirīya Brāhmaṇa</em>&rsquo;s <em>prathamāṣṭaka</em> call <em>kṛttikā</em> the &ldquo;mouth of <em>nakṣatra</em>-s&rdquo;. The first <em>mantra</em> from <em>dvitīyaprapāṭhaka</em> says <em>kṛttikā</em> is <em><strong>अग्नेर्नक्षत्रम्</strong></em> and <em><strong>मुखं वा एतन्नक्षत्राणाम्</strong></em>. Then from the seventh <em>mantra</em> of <em>pañcamaprapāṭhaka</em>, <em>kṛttikā</em> is the <em><strong>prathama</strong></em> of the <em>devanakṣatra</em>-s. What this means is the vernal equnox in the ancient times fell during <em>kṛttikā</em>. This would put the winter solstice in <em>maghā</em>. This is supported by the fact that in <em>Taittirīya Saṇhitā</em>, from <em>ṣaṣṭhaprapāṭhaka</em>, <em>caturthānuvāka</em> eighth <em>mantra</em>, you can deduce that <em>Māgha paurṇamī</em>, that is <em>Māgha</em>&rsquo;s full moon was the beginning of the new year, meaning at this time, the winter solstice. <em>Mīmānsaka</em>-s like Jaimini and his followers have concluded as much. Even further, few scholars have postulated that <em>vishākhā</em> gets its name because it was the <em>nakṣatra</em> that got &ldquo;cut&rdquo; or &ldquo;branched&rdquo; due to the equinoxal line cutting it, because it is opposing <em>kṛttikā</em> and would have marked the autumnal equinox. It does not have to be a mathematically equal bisection, merely a cut through at any division.</p>
<p>The full discussion on this is extremenly dense, covering several commentaries, which cannot all be reproduced without essentially writting the entire chapter itself, hence it has been summarized to cover only the conclusions. Next we will discuss how an even older tradition states that <em>mṛgashīrṣā</em> marked the vernal equniox.</p>
<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on first two chapters from Lokamanya Tilak&#39;s Orion</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/003-notes-on-orion-two-chaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2023 09:58:29 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/003-notes-on-orion-two-chaps/</guid>
      <description>At two instances in Mahābharata, Bhīṣma&amp;rsquo;s standard, the symbols of his flag are described. Once as five stars and sun (CE 4.3.50) and second as five stars and a palm tree (CE 6.4.44). We are not told the significance of these symbols, nor can we infer anything from within the story of Mahābhārata as to why Bhīṣma would have chosen them. Whatever can be guessed is with the knowledge of the larger vaidika mythology and in refernce to Dyaus Pitṛ, or simply Dyou in Mahābhārata, who is one of the 8 vasu-s who was cursed to be born as a mortal.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At two instances in Mahābharata, Bhīṣma&rsquo;s standard, the symbols of his flag are described. Once as five stars and sun (CE 4.3.50) and second as five stars and a palm tree (CE 6.4.44). We are not told the significance of these symbols, nor can we infer anything from <em>within</em> the story of Mahābhārata as to why Bhīṣma would have chosen them. Whatever can be guessed is with the knowledge of the larger <em>vaidika</em> mythology and in refernce to Dyaus Pitṛ, or simply Dyou in Mahābhārata, who is one of the 8 <em>vasu</em>-s who was cursed to be born as a mortal. Dyou was born as Bhīṣma, the son of Gaṇgā and Shantanu (CE 1.7.93). Dyaus and Bhīṣma share similarities in that they are both said to be a &ldquo;grandfather&rdquo; figure in their respective domains, are larger than life entities and for Bhīṣma specifically, he is one of the last remanents of older Kaurava-s who links with the Pāṇdava-s. It is on this backdrop that the five stars (and the one version with sun) start making sense: Bhīṣma is representing the sky on his standard, as that is his domain.</p>
<p>I had asked this question to a learned person, and he theorized that it might have something to do with the planets that were observed very early on, excluding the Sun and the Moon, viz., Venus, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn and possibly Mercury, though its proximity to the Sun makes it harder to spot. I inquired if this theory is based on a book which this individual adores very much, written by <em>Lokamānya</em> Tilak, titled <strong>&ldquo;The Orion Or Researches Into The Antiquity Of The Vedas&rdquo;</strong>. The book was published in 1893, during the same time in which many other books on Hindu cultural studies that were being translated into English after the British colonization had taken full effect were being published. Tilak himself postulates a date for the Veda-s, more specifically the <em>vaidika</em> texts such as <em>saṇhitā</em>-s, etc., using the internal astronomical (or astrological) references from these texts. The person said yes, but while I have found nothing related to the five stars/planets in the book so far, it is a fantastic and enlightening read nonetheless.</p>
<p>The accuracy of Tilak&rsquo;s work aside, the actual information within it is extremely useful, especially since such subjects are not discussed widely (any more atleast), owing to either unacceptance of non-traditional analysis of the <em>shāstra</em>-s or general ignorance. It comprises comments and discussions by various scholars, ancient and modern on these astronomical references and how they changed (or remained the same).</p>
<p>The cosmos is always in motion, which the concept of <em>ṛta</em> aptly conveys. The motions of the celestial bodies and seasons were very much understood by extremely ancient <em>ārya</em>-s, and they built their long-term rituals like the <strong><em>samvatsara satra</em></strong> accordingly. This is a <em>yajña</em> mentioned in the <em>Aitareya Brāhmaṇa</em>&rsquo;s 4th <em>pañcikā</em> and is described in enough detail for us to infer that the <em>satra</em> corresponded and extended to one whole year. It started on the beginning of a new year, and each major phase of the <em>yajña</em> lasted for 6 months, at which pont it was split by a <em>viṣuvantaḥ</em> or <em>viṣuvān</em>, and the ritual carried on for another 6 months until the end of the year.</p>
<p>What is fascinating about this is when exactly did the year begin in these ancient times. While today different regions celebrate beginning of a traditional new year in different months like <em>Āshvina</em> or <em>Kārtika</em> or <em>Caitra</em>, etc., it is generally accepted that 12 months are divided into <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> and <em>dakṣināyana</em>, which basically mean that the Sun travels northwards and southwards (in the sky) for a period of six months each. The day these transitions happen are called the solstices. Currently, there is a discrepancy as to when <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> actually begins, but it still does not indiciate the beginning of a new year.</p>
<p><em>Uttarāyaṇa</em> as a phase is associated with the time of <em>devatā</em>-s, and all auspicious ceremonies (like <em>upanayana saṇskāra</em>) are performed in this period. <em>Dakṣināyana</em> is associated with the time of <em>pitṛ</em>-s, or Yama and all funeral related ceremonies (<em>shrāddha</em>) are part of these 6 months. As it is right now, the seasons of <em>Shishira</em>, <em>Vasanta</em> and <em>Grīṣma</em> make the first phase and <em>Varṣā</em>, <em>Sharada</em> and <em>Hemanta</em> make the second. <strong>BUT</strong>, in <em>Shatapatha Brāhmaṇa</em>&rsquo;s 2nd <em>khaṇḍa</em>, we have the following <em>mantra</em>-s:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>वसन्तो ग्रीष्मो वर्षाः। ते देवा ऋतवः शरद्धेमन्तः शिशिरस्ते पितरो य एवापूर्यतेऽर्धमासः स देवा योऽपक्षीयते स पितरोऽहरेव देवा रात्रिः पितरः पुनरह्नः पूर्वाह्णो देवा अपराह्णः पितरः ।१।</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>ते वा एत ऋतवः। देवाः पितरः स यो हैवं विद्वान्देवाः पितर इति ह्वयत्या हास्य देवा देवहूयं गचन्त्या पितरः पितृहूयमवन्ति हैनं देवा देवहूये ऽवन्ति पितरः पितृहूये य एवं विद्वान्देवाः पितर इति ह्वयति ।२।</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>स यत्रोदगावर्तते। देवेषु तर्हि भवति देवांस्तर्ह्यभिगोपायत्यथ यत्र दक्षिणावर्तते पितृषु तर्हि भवति पितॄंस्तर्ह्यभिगोपायति ।३।</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>वसन्तो ग्रीष्मो वर्षाः। ते देवा ऋतवः शरद्धेमन्तः शिशिरस्ते पितरो</strong>, this part of <em>mantra</em> expressely states which seasons belong, or belonged, to which entity. The idea of these three months being the <em>devatā</em> seasons is essentially the same as <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> being the phase of the <em>devatā</em>-s. Same of the next three for <em>pitṛ</em>-s.</p>
<p>This is <em>only</em> possible when the year is divided along the equinoxes, the vernal and autumnal. The word <em>viṣuvantaḥ</em> from earlier is made up of &ldquo;<em>viṣu</em>&rdquo; (equally, on both sides) and &ldquo;<em>-vantaḥ</em>&rdquo; (full of, having), hence literally meaning &ldquo;having equal halves&rdquo;, which in terms of an year is a division of 6 months, and keeping inline with the above <em>mantra</em>-s, this division should happen at the equinoxes. We now have express testimony of ancient texts to strongly assert that very early on, the <em>vaidika</em>-s celebrated the beginning of a new year on the vernal equinox.</p>
<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dashavatara-s and the Human Evolution</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/001-dashavata/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 14:05:42 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/001-dashavata/</guid>
      <description>In Bharat, the religion developed along side the civilization. Hence, it is difficult to make any distinctions between the two. For this reason, Bharat&amp;rsquo;s science is both religious and, well, &amp;ldquo;scientific&amp;rdquo;. There is Science of War, Science of Language, Science of Astronomy, Science of Living Beings, etc. If you have had an interest in Hinduism and spent anytime reading articles on it or following pages that post about Hinduism and it&amp;rsquo;s glory, you have likely come across the &amp;ldquo;Dashavatara-Evolution Theory&amp;rdquo;.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In Bharat, the religion developed along side the civilization. Hence, it is difficult to make any distinctions between the two. For this reason, Bharat&rsquo;s science is both religious and, well, &ldquo;scientific&rdquo;. There is Science of War, Science of Language, Science of Astronomy, Science of Living Beings, etc. If you have had an interest in Hinduism and spent anytime reading articles on it or following pages that post about Hinduism and it&rsquo;s glory, you have likely come across the &ldquo;Dashavatara-Evolution Theory&rdquo;. And on the surface, it makes a lot of sense. But does this fit well theologically?</p>
<p>For those unfamiliar with the theory, it goes this way: The ten great avatars of Bhagavan Vishnu represent human evolution, from sea dwelling organisms to peak enlightenment. Hence, the Matsya Avatara represents the micro-organism that evolved in water. Following the fish form, you have the Kurma Avatara which reprensents the adaptation of life to sustain itself on both land and water. Varaha Avatara repesents the complete evolution to land dwelling animal and Narsimha Avatara represents the transition of animal to man. The Vamana and &ldquo;Parshu&rdquo; Rama Avataras are supposed to represent the primitive man, while Ramachandra and Vasudeva Krishna are supposed to represent the civilized. Finally, the Buddha Avatara is humanity at it&rsquo;s height of intelligence and learning, waiting for the eventual decline that will be brought by Kalki Avatara. This seems very logical and &ldquo;scientific&rdquo;, right? Well, let&rsquo;s take a look.</p>
<p>The theory first assumes that Hinduism&rsquo;s concept of time is the same as how we percieve it now. There&rsquo;s a beginning, a middle, and then there&rsquo;s an end. After the end, we are not sure what happenes. But the theological explanation is that there is a beginning again. The time measurements range from a Kshana to Kalpa, which is a gigantic measurement of time according to which the &ldquo;scientific&rdquo; age of Earth is relatively very young. Not only that, time never ceases to exist, just as the Jivatma or the Paramatma. They are infinite. There is no beginning, there is no middle and there is no end here. Why do I bring this up? Well, because, by modern calculations, millions and millions of years elapse between successive avataras and they take place in not just different Mahayugas but also Manavantaras. Not only that, these ten reincarnations are just the most popular ones. The Bhagavata Purana mentions 22 avataras! If we keep the puranas aside for a while, the list still misses out on the Narayana avatara of Vishnu which predates both the Ramas (quite possibly Vamana too) and is mentioned countless times in the Mahabharata.</p>
<p>Then we must ask ourselves, what is the theory actually based on? Is it based on biology? Or morals and enlightenment? If it is based on biology, then one can stop at &ldquo;Parashu&rdquo; Rama (and Vamana too but let&rsquo;s put him aside since he was a dwarf and a defect can be pointed out) because he is not a &ldquo;primitive&rdquo; man, rather he is a hermit, a renunciate in many aspects. He is famous for the destruction of Sahasrabahu Kartavirya Arjuna, who was a king of a then strong kingdom. Not only that, the theory does not take into account Mohini avatara, which came to be about the same time as Kurma avatara. Mohini is the female reincarnation of Vishnu to decieve Asuras. No, the list cannot be based on biology then.</p>
<p>So it is based on morals and enlightenment? Ok, why should we not stop at Vamana then? Vamana, though child he was during his confrontation with Bali, later on went to establish many hermitages. Should he be not considered enlightened? Ramachandra is hailed as the best of the Ikshavaku dynasty and also one of the greatest kings to ever rule. His sacrifices and sufferings were for Dharma. Does he not have the most sacrosanct morality? What about Bhagavan Krishna then? Time after time, since his birth, he has been hailed as the being who sustains everything that exists. He was the one who imparted his teachings to the world through the Mahabharata. Or Krishna Dvaipayana Veda Vyasa, who did great serice to the Dharmic compositions and literature. Are they not enlightened beyond human conceptions then? Another thing to consider is that Siddhartha Gautama, the Buddha, was listed as an avatara of Vishnu much later on, much closer to our times.</p>
<p>If one finds delight in believing this theory, I am no one to change their minds. It does make a lot of sense at a strech. But as with most deeply religious things that people desperately try to explain with the modern scientific views, this one has many holes and is straight up wrong at times.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanatana Dharma: Religion or Civilization?</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/002-religionorciv/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 14:37:44 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/002-religionorciv/</guid>
      <description>History has always been a very intriguing subject. It&amp;rsquo;s a portal to the past based on imprints left by natural forces or great civilizations and subsequently great empires. While remnants left by natural forces help us understand the Earth, the ones by civilizations help us understand the man of the past. Their behavior, society, beliefs et cetera. Any read through of history, and you shall come around some common names. Such as Romans, Greeks, Egyptians, Chinese and the Indians.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>History has always been a very intriguing subject. It&rsquo;s a portal to the past based on imprints left by natural forces or great civilizations and subsequently great empires. While remnants left by natural forces help us understand the Earth, the ones by civilizations help us understand the man of the past. Their behavior, society, beliefs et cetera. Any read through of history, and you shall come around some common names. Such as Romans, Greeks, Egyptians, Chinese and the Indians. While smaller civilizations existed everywhere like in parts of South Iraq, earlier known as Sumeria or the indigenous society of then undiscovered North America, the ones mentioned earlier have had a massive impacts in their respective regions and sometimes even dictate the the traditions that have been passed down to the present. While it is debatable which civilization came first, a rather unwarranted debate actually because of the difference of regions and cultures, all these civilizations have existed for millennia. But none of the earlier civilizations have survived to witness the present world or have their ethics survived. All except the Indian, or the Dharmic civilization.</p>
<p>It is agreed upon the fact that the region of Indus Valley, or Sindh as the ancient Indians called it, is the cradle of Indian Civilization. The society was built upon the rivers Sindhu and Saraswati. Hence it is also referred to as &ldquo;Saraswati-Sindhu&rdquo; Civilization. The cities of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro were the first settlements of the civilization and have left their imprints not only in the area itself but other civilizations they had their relations with. Sometime later on, Rakhigarhi became central to the civilization. Now, a baseless argument and a great misconception is that some time later, these settlements &ldquo;vanished&rdquo; from the face of the Ancient India and soon after the &ldquo;Aryans invaded&rdquo; the Northern regions of the sub-continent &ldquo;bringing India it&rsquo;s culture&rdquo;. The Aryan Invasion theory has been debunked many times: archaeologically, genealogically, linguistically and all other -allies possible, and hence has been toned down to the &ldquo;Aryan Migration&rdquo; theory. What even? I will not shit on the theory here but you can just search for it on YouTube. You can watch these for starters: Presentation by Dr. Raj Vedam, Presentation by Dr. Abhijit Chavda and Panel Discussion about the theory.</p>
<p>With the stupid stuff out of the way, let&rsquo;s get to the point. The Hindu civilization has been one of the most powerful civilizations throughout history. This is indicated by the numerous historic records which were made obscure by Western historians for a long time. Indians dominated the whole of South-Eastern Asia including countries like the present day Afghanistan (referred to as Gandhara in Hindu texts), Pakistan, Nepal, Bangladesh and parts of Myanmar, Bhutan, Cambodia, Indonesia and Philippines in later periods. And of course, including the present day India. Not only that, the Dharmic ethics of ancient India have influenced religions other part of Eastern Asia. A moderate-read of ancient Hindu texts clearly point to the fact that religious philosophy and social order were intermixed with each other and one influenced the other. A few instances include the Itihasa texts of Indian literature. Ithasa literally means &ldquo;thus-it-happened&rdquo; in Sanskrit and are regarded to have historical authority. The two Itihasa texts, Ramayana and Mahabharata are not only some of the greatest stories ever told but also historical records of how the society was in their times. The other scriptures such as the Vedas and Puranas have their own historical authenticity but their theological side is embraced more than the historical. A thorough read-through the corpus of Hindu literature helps us imagine the civilization of the old. Their behaviors, society, beliefs et cetera.</p>
<p>But in the times of now, these practices have been just rendered as a religion. There is indeed truth to that attribution but Ethics of War, A Social Order through the Varna-Jaati System, The Rules of Ruling, Preservation of Nature et cetera are all non-religious aspects of the society which are derived from the theology itself. These all strive for Dharma, a very nuanced word whose meaning and never be captured by western languages. A disregard of the Vedic principles would mean disregarding the entire civilization. And it&rsquo;s not as if the Indian Civilization was weak. It is strong. Kings and Emperors commanded large armies and dominated large portions of the nation. Yes, indeed, there was a nation. There was no centralized government (rather there have been Emperors who dominated the ancient land), but there was a common culture. From north to south, the civilization followed common ethics and did only differ in the names of kingdoms. They followed Dharma.</p>
<p>The sciences, art forms, languages, laws and life-style of the common man all derive themselves from the Vedic truth. Of course, that&rsquo;s not to say literally every single thing has it&rsquo;s basis in the Vedas but the most important aspects do. And these traditions have survived the onslaught of various invasions and foreign corruptions. The credit for this lies with none other but the Indians themselves. Common folk preserving their ways of life, Kings preserving common folk, the Acharyas preserving the Vedas amongst other things contributed to the survival of the culture. It sought this as their Dharma.</p>
<p>To be born in this civilization and realize it&rsquo;s grandeur, I believe it is my Dharma contribute in any way I can. How about writing a blogs on this topic for starters, eh?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/useful-links/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 1922 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/useful-links/</guid>
      <description>Brāhmaṇa-s ब्राह्मणाः • Aitareya Brāhmaṇa ऐतरेयब्राह्मण Volume 1 Dr. Sudhakar Malaviya
• Aitareya Brāhmaṇa ऐतरेयब्राह्मण Volume 2 Dr. Sudhakar Malaviya
• Shatapatha Brāhmaṇa शतपथ ब्राह्मण English
• Shatapatha Brāhmaṇa शतपथ ब्राह्मण माध्यन्दिनशाखा Volume 1
• Shatapatha Brāhmaṇa शतपथ ब्राह्मण माध्यन्दिनशाखा Volume 2
Miscellaneous अन्य • Indian Culture Government Site
• Willbourhall Mathematics and Mathematical Astronomy
• Devavani Sanskrit Radio
• Wikimedia Commons (for images)
• Heritage of Dhruva the Pole Star (YouTube video)</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="brāhmaṇa-s-बरहमण">Brāhmaṇa-s ब्राह्मणाः</h2>
<p>• <a href="https://vedicheritage.gov.in/flipbook/Aitareya_Brahmana_Vol_I/">Aitareya Brāhmaṇa ऐतरेयब्राह्मण Volume 1 Dr. Sudhakar Malaviya</a></p>
<p>• <a href="https://vedicheritage.gov.in/flipbook/Aitareya_Brahmana_Vol_II/">Aitareya Brāhmaṇa ऐतरेयब्राह्मण Volume 2 Dr. Sudhakar Malaviya</a></p>
<p>• <a href="https://sacred-texts.com/hin/sbr/index.htm">Shatapatha Brāhmaṇa शतपथ ब्राह्मण English</a></p>
<p>• <a href="https://vedicheritage.gov.in/flipbook/Shatpatha_Brahmana_Mandhyandina_Vol-I/">Shatapatha Brāhmaṇa शतपथ ब्राह्मण माध्यन्दिनशाखा Volume 1</a></p>
<p>• <a href="https://vedicheritage.gov.in/flipbook/Shatpatha_Brahmana_Mandhyandina_Vol-II/">Shatapatha Brāhmaṇa शतपथ ब्राह्मण माध्यन्दिनशाखा Volume 2</a></p>
<h2 id="miscellaneous-अनय">Miscellaneous अन्य</h2>
<p>• <a href="https://www.indianculture.gov.in/">Indian Culture Government Site</a></p>
<p>• <a href="https://www.wilbourhall.org/">Willbourhall Mathematics and Mathematical Astronomy</a></p>
<p>• <a href="https://devavanisanskritradio.org/">Devavani Sanskrit Radio</a></p>
<p>• <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Main_Page">Wikimedia Commons</a> (for images)</p>
<p>• <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0whFX4GuoJg&amp;ab_channel=TaralayaBangalore">Heritage of Dhruva the Pole Star</a> (YouTube video)</p>
<p>• <a href="https://archive.org/details/FZVp_nagari-pracharini-patrika-54-kashi-nagari-pracharini-sabha/mode/1up?view=theater">नागरीप्रचारिणी पत्रिका</a></p>
<p>• <a href="https://www.packolkata.gov.in/index.php">Positional Astronomy Center</a></p>
<p>• <a href="https://archive.org/details/divyastras_of_kurukshetrawar_dipavali_debroy/page/n8/mode/1up?view=theater">Divyastras of Mahabharata</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>