<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Shrama</title>
    <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Shrama</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Raunack Tripathi</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 11:51:36 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Blessing and Gratefulness in Rāmāyaṇa</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/005-ramayana-blessing-gratefulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 11:51:36 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/005-ramayana-blessing-gratefulness/</guid>
      <description>That the shāstra-s continuously refer to events that transpired before them is a well-known attribute. Protagonists of a story will be refered to as &amp;ldquo;narendra&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;rājendra&amp;rdquo;, etc., other such epithets which invoke Indra as a superlative, him being the king of deva-s.
There are smaller such incidents, which are just presented as off-handed comments, but are extremely deep and have entire histories attached to them. One such instance is when Rāma is about to leave for the forest, to being his vanavāsa, his grief-stricken mother, Kausalyā pronounces many blessings on him.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>That the <em>shāstra</em>-s continuously refer to events that transpired before them is a well-known attribute. Protagonists of a story will be refered to as &ldquo;<em>narendra</em>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<em>rājendra</em>&rdquo;, etc., other such epithets which invoke Indra as a superlative, him being the king of <em>deva</em>-s.</p>
<p>There are smaller such incidents, which are just presented as off-handed comments, but are extremely deep and have entire histories attached to them. One such instance is when Rāma is about to leave for the forest, to being his <em>vanavāsa</em>, his grief-stricken mother, Kausalyā pronounces many blessings on him. She says, amongst other things:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>यन्मङ्गलं सहस्राक्षे सर्वदेवनमस्कृते। वृत्रनाशे समभवत्तत्ते भवतु मङ्गलम्॥</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>यन्मङ्गलं सुपर्णस्य विनताकल्पयत्पुरा। अमृतं प्रार्थयानस्य तत्ते भवतु मङ्गलम्॥</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Roughly translated as : &ldquo;Which ever auspicious portents occured to the thousand-eyed one when he destroyed Vṛtra, may those occur to you as well. Whatever auspiciouness Vinatā prayed for Suparṇa when he endeavored for <em>amṛta</em>, may those auspicious protents happen to you as well.&rdquo; While Indra&rsquo;s destruction of Vṛtra is among the greatest of <em>ārya</em> stories, acquiring new meanings and forms over long periods of time, Vinatā&rsquo;s story is comparable to Kausalyā&rsquo;s helplessness and they both share a concern for their son, endeavoring on a perilous journey.</p>
<p>Vinatā and Kadrū were the wives of Kashyapa, and the former is the mother of Garuḍa and Aruṇa, while the latter is the mother of all <em>sarpa</em>-s and <em>nāga</em>-s. Vinatā and Kadrū placed a bet, on whether Uccaishravā&rsquo;s tail is black or white. Vinatā said it to be white and Kadrū said it to be black. Considering Uccaishravā is a white horse, naturally all of his parts would also be white. So a case can be made that Kadrū does not know her current affairs. Irregardless, they put on this wager, went over to check on the all-white-horse-with-nothing-black-on-him and Kadrū cheated by asking her sons, the snakes to cover Uccaishravā&rsquo;s tail, which made it appear black in color, thus &ldquo;defeating&rdquo; Vinatā. The condition was whoever was wrong in her guess, would become the slave of the other. Hence Vinatā was now Kadrū&rsquo;s slave.</p>
<p>Kadrū and her sons began to order Vinatā and Garuḍa around accordingly. Needless to say that the latter pair was dejected and after a few adventures of unreasonable requests, Garuḍa asks his half-brothers what would it take to be freed from this slavery. The <em>sarpa</em>-s replied that if Garuḍa bring to them the <em>amṛta</em> of the <em>deva</em>-s from <em>svarga</em>, he and his mother would be free. Garuḍa relayed the same to his mother who pronounced the following blessings unto him:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>पक्षौ ते मारुतः पातु चन्द्रः पृष्ठं तु पुत्रक। शिरस्तु पातु ते वह्निर्भास्करः सर्वमेव तु॥</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Meaning: &ldquo;Let the Maruts protect your wings. O son! Let the moon protect your back. Let the fire protect your head. Let the sun protect all your body.&rdquo; And also that she would always pray to bring him welfare. Saying that these prayers &ldquo;worked&rdquo; is an understatement. Both Garuḍa and Rāma would bring nothing but destruction to their enemies after their endeavors. Garuḍa also became the <em>vāhana</em> of Viṣṇu.</p>
<p>In another instance, <em>pravacanakāra</em>-s to justify Rāma&rsquo;s quality of being &ldquo;<em>kṛtajña</em>&rdquo; (Rāmāyaṇa 1.1.2) cite a story from Bhāgavata Purāṇa. In the 6th <em>adhyāya</em> of 9th <em>skandha</em>, the Ikṣvāku <em>vansha</em> is described. One king of this lineage is Puraṅjaya. The <em>devatā</em>-s and <em>dānava</em>-s were at it again, you know the usual, and they request help from Puraṅjaya. The latter agreed on the condition that Indra would become his <em>vāhana</em>. Indra obviously refuses at first but the at behest Viṣṇu agrees. Indra takes the form of a bull, and Puraṅjaya sits on his back, <em>kukud</em>. They won their fight against the <em>dānava</em>-s and since Puraṅjaya had sat on the back of Indra, he came to be known as Kakutstha, meaning &lsquo;stationed on back&rsquo;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>पुरंजयस्तस्य सुत इन्द्रवाह इतीरितः। ककुत्स्थ इति चाप्युक्तः शृणु नामानि कर्मभिः॥</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Since Rāma descends from Puraṅjaya, he is called &ldquo;<em>Kākutstha</em>&rdquo;, much like how he is called &ldquo;Dāsharathi&rdquo; and &ldquo;Rāghava&rdquo;, thus expressing gratitute to Indra and his ancestor.</p>
<p>These are small things, but a little curiosity goes a long way.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on third chapter from Lokamanya Tilak&#39;s Orion</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/004-notes-on-orion-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 06:02:51 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/004-notes-on-orion-3/</guid>
      <description>Continuing from notes from the first two chapters, though very early on vaidika-s did start their year at the vernal equinox, the tradition shifted to starting the new year at the winter solstice, or what uttarāyaṇa has been representing in our times so far. When and why this happened, we do not know. What I can postulate is that when vaidika-s would&amp;rsquo;ve realized that entire seasons were changing after hundreds of years during the equinoxes, that is to say, the vernal equinox which took place in an asterism that marked the beginning of spring, but now this asterism falls in winter, they would have gone for something more perceptible like the motion of the Sun in the sky, to create a celestial marker for their rituals.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Continuing from <a href="https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/003-notes-on-orion-two-chaps/">notes from the first two chapters</a>, though very early on <em>vaidika</em>-s did start their year at the vernal equinox, the tradition shifted to starting the new year at the winter solstice, or what <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> has been representing in our times so far. When and why this happened, we do not know. What I can postulate is that when <em>vaidika</em>-s would&rsquo;ve realized that entire seasons were changing after hundreds of years during the equinoxes, that is to say, the vernal equinox which took place in an asterism that marked the beginning of spring, but now this asterism falls in winter, they would have gone for something more perceptible like the motion of the Sun in the sky, to create a celestial marker for their rituals. However, I have not come across any scholarly thought to support this.</p>
<p>The point remains, the <em>ārambhaṇīya</em> of the <em>samvatsara satra</em> changed from the day of vernal equinox to winter solstice. Currently, the vernal equinox passes through <em>revatī</em>, but has receded by several degrees. Even still, the vernal equinox falls around 23rd September, in <em>Bhādrapada</em>. This puts the winter solstice, and the beginning of <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> roughly in <em>mṛgashīrṣā</em>, consequently in month of <em>Mārgashīrṣa</em>. However the <em>uttarāyaṇa</em>, in conjuction with <em>makara saṅkrānti</em> is celebrated in the month of <em>Pauṣa</em>. Following articles by <a href="https://koenraadelst.blogspot.com/2020/12/the-real-uttarayana.html">Koenraad Elst</a> and <a href="https://pragyata.com/when-should-pongal-makar-samkranti-be-celebrated-and-why/">A K Kaul</a> go in to details and discussions on this subject. Whatever be the tradition of dates, the tradition of principle dictates we consider <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> to fall in <em>Mārgashīrṣa</em>. However, considering the antiquity of <em>shāstra</em>-s, there would have been a time when the equinox and solstice fell later than it does, and ritual timings would have followed these markers. This is indeed the case.</p>
<p>Firstly, there are grounds to believe that <em>kṛttikā</em>, and NOT <em>ashvinī</em>, was the first in the list of <em>nakṣatra</em>-s. The <em>mantra</em>-s from <em>Taittirīya Brāhmaṇa</em>&rsquo;s <em>prathamāṣṭaka</em> call <em>kṛttikā</em> the &ldquo;mouth of <em>nakṣatra</em>-s&rdquo;. The first <em>mantra</em> from <em>dvitīyaprapāṭhaka</em> says <em>kṛttikā</em> is <em><strong>अग्नेर्नक्षत्रम्</strong></em> and <em><strong>मुखं वा एतन्नक्षत्राणाम्</strong></em>. Then from the seventh <em>mantra</em> of <em>pañcamaprapāṭhaka</em>, <em>kṛttikā</em> is the <em><strong>prathama</strong></em> of the <em>devanakṣatra</em>-s. What this means is the vernal equnox in the ancient times fell during <em>kṛttikā</em>. This would put the winter solstice in <em>maghā</em>. This is supported by the fact that in <em>Taittirīya Saṇhitā</em>, from <em>caturthaprapāṭhaka</em>&rsquo;s eighth <em>mantra</em>, you can dedude that <em>Māgha paurṇamī</em>, that is <em>Māgha</em>&rsquo;s full moon was the beginning of the new year, meaning at this time, the winter solstice. <em>Mīmānsaka</em>-s like Jaimini and his followers have concluded as much. Even further, few scholars have postulated that <em>vishākhā</em> gets its name because it was the <em>nakṣatra</em> that got &ldquo;cut&rdquo; or &ldquo;branched&rdquo; due to the equinoxal line cutting it, because it is opposing <em>kṛttikā</em> and would have marked the autumnal equinox. It does not have to be a mathematically equal bisection, merely a cut through at any division.</p>
<p>The full discussion on this is extremenly dense, covering several commentaries, which cannot all be reproduced without essentially writting the entire chapter itself, hence it has been summarized to cover only the conclusions. Next we will discuss how an even older tradition states that <em>mṛgashīrṣā</em> marked the vernal equniox.</p>
<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on first two chapters from Lokamanya Tilak&#39;s Orion</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/003-notes-on-orion-two-chaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2023 09:58:29 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/003-notes-on-orion-two-chaps/</guid>
      <description>At two instances in Mahābharata, Bhīṣma&amp;rsquo;s standard, the symbols of his flag are described. Once as five stars and sun (CE 4.3.50) and second as five stars and a palm tree (CE 6.4.44). We are not told the significance of these symbols, nor can we infer anything from within the story of Mahābhārata as to why Bhīṣma would have chosen them. Whatever can be guessed is with the knowledge of the larger vaidika mythology and in refernce to Dyaus Pitṛ, or simply Dyou in Mahābhārata, who is one of the 8 vasu-s who was cursed to be born as a mortal.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At two instances in Mahābharata, Bhīṣma&rsquo;s standard, the symbols of his flag are described. Once as five stars and sun (CE 4.3.50) and second as five stars and a palm tree (CE 6.4.44). We are not told the significance of these symbols, nor can we infer anything from <em>within</em> the story of Mahābhārata as to why Bhīṣma would have chosen them. Whatever can be guessed is with the knowledge of the larger <em>vaidika</em> mythology and in refernce to Dyaus Pitṛ, or simply Dyou in Mahābhārata, who is one of the 8 <em>vasu</em>-s who was cursed to be born as a mortal. Dyou was born as Bhīṣma, the son of Gaṇgā and Shantanu (CE 1.7.93). Dyaus and Bhīṣma share similarities in that they are both said to be a &ldquo;grandfather&rdquo; figure in their respective domains, are larger than life entities and for Bhīṣma specifically, he is one of the last remanents of older Kaurava-s who links with the Pāṇdava-s. It is on this backdrop that the five stars (and the one version with sun) start making sense: Bhīṣma is representing the sky on his standard, as that is his domain.</p>
<p>I had asked this question to a learned person, and he theorized that it might have something to do with the planets that were observed very early on, excluding the Sun and the Moon, viz., Venus, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn and possibly Mercury, though its proximity to the Sun makes it harder to spot. I inquired if this theory is based on a book which this individual adores very much, written by <em>Lokamānya</em> Tilak, titled <strong>&ldquo;The Orion Or Researches Into The Antiquity Of The Vedas&rdquo;</strong>. The book was published in 1893, during the same time in which many other books on Hindu cultural studies that were being translated into English after the British colonization had taken full effect were being published. Tilak himself postulates a date for the Veda-s, more specifically the <em>vaidika</em> texts such as <em>saṇhitā</em>-s, etc., using the internal astronomical (or astrological) references from these texts. The person said yes, but while I have found nothing related to the five stars/planets in the book so far, it is a fantastic and enlightening read nonetheless.</p>
<p>The accuracy of Tilak&rsquo;s work aside, the actual information within it is extremely useful, especially since such subjects are not discussed widely (any more atleast), owing to either unacceptance of non-traditional analysis of the <em>shāstra</em>-s or general ignorance. It comprises comments and discussions by various scholars, ancient and modern on these astronomical references and how they changed (or remained the same).</p>
<p>The cosmos is always in motion, which the concept of <em>ṛta</em> aptly conveys. The motions of the celestial bodies and seasons were very much understood by extremely ancient <em>ārya</em>-s, and they built their long-term rituals like the <strong><em>samvatsara satra</em></strong> accordingly. This is a <em>yajña</em> mentioned in the <em>Aitareya Brāhmaṇa</em>&rsquo;s 4th <em>pañcikā</em> and is described in enough detail for us to infer that the <em>satra</em> corresponded and extended to one whole year. It started on the beginning of a new year, and each major phase of the <em>yajña</em> lasted for 6 months, at which pont it was split by a <em>viṣuvantaḥ</em> or <em>viṣuvān</em>, and the ritual carried on for another 6 months until the end of the year.</p>
<p>What is fascinating about this is when exactly did the year begin in these ancient times. While today different regions celebrate beginning of a traditional new year in different months like <em>Āshvina</em> or <em>Kārtika</em> or <em>Caitra</em>, etc., it is generally accepted that 12 months are divided into <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> and <em>dakṣināyana</em>, which basically mean that the Sun travels northwards and southwards (in the sky) for a period of six months each. The day these transitions happen are called the solstices. Currently, there is a discrepancy as to when <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> actually begins, but it still does not indiciate the beginning of a new year.</p>
<p><em>Uttarāyaṇa</em> as a phase is associated with the time of <em>devatā</em>-s, and all auspicious ceremonies (like <em>upanayana saṇskāra</em>) are performed in this period. <em>Dakṣināyana</em> is associated with the time of <em>pitṛ</em>-s, or Yama and all funeral related ceremonies (<em>shrāddha</em>) are part of these 6 months. As it is right now, the seasons of <em>Shishira</em>, <em>Vasanta</em> and <em>Grīṣma</em> make the first phase and <em>Varṣā</em>, <em>Sharada</em> and <em>Hemanta</em> make the second. <strong>BUT</strong>, in <em>Shatapatha Brāhmaṇa</em>&rsquo;s 2nd <em>khaṇḍa</em>, we have the following <em>mantra</em>-s:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>वसन्तो ग्रीष्मो वर्षाः। ते देवा ऋतवः शरद्धेमन्तः शिशिरस्ते पितरो य एवापूर्यतेऽर्धमासः स देवा योऽपक्षीयते स पितरोऽहरेव देवा रात्रिः पितरः पुनरह्नः पूर्वाह्णो देवा अपराह्णः पितरः ।१।</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>ते वा एत ऋतवः। देवाः पितरः स यो हैवं विद्वान्देवाः पितर इति ह्वयत्या हास्य देवा देवहूयं गचन्त्या पितरः पितृहूयमवन्ति हैनं देवा देवहूये ऽवन्ति पितरः पितृहूये य एवं विद्वान्देवाः पितर इति ह्वयति ।२।</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>स यत्रोदगावर्तते। देवेषु तर्हि भवति देवांस्तर्ह्यभिगोपायत्यथ यत्र दक्षिणावर्तते पितृषु तर्हि भवति पितॄंस्तर्ह्यभिगोपायति ।३।</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>वसन्तो ग्रीष्मो वर्षाः। ते देवा ऋतवः शरद्धेमन्तः शिशिरस्ते पितरो</strong>, this part of <em>mantra</em> expressely states which seasons belong, or belonged, to which entity. The idea of these three months being the <em>devatā</em> seasons is essentially the same as <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> being the phase of the <em>devatā</em>-s. Same of the next three for <em>pitṛ</em>-s.</p>
<p>This is <em>only</em> possible when the year is divided along the equinoxes, the vernal and autumnal. The word <em>viṣuvantaḥ</em> from earlier is made up of &ldquo;<em>viṣu</em>&rdquo; (equally, on both sides) and &ldquo;<em>-vantaḥ</em>&rdquo; (full of, having), hence literally meaning &ldquo;having equal halves&rdquo;, which in terms of an year is a division of 6 months, and keeping inline with the above <em>mantra</em>-s, this division should happen at the equinoxes. We now have express testimony of ancient texts to strongly assert that very early on, the <em>vaidika</em>-s celebrated the beginning of a new year on the vernal equinox.</p>
<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dashavatara-s and the Human Evolution</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/001-dashavata/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 14:05:42 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/001-dashavata/</guid>
      <description>In Bharat, the religion developed along side the civilization. Hence, it is difficult to make any distinctions between the two. For this reason, Bharat&amp;rsquo;s science is both religious and, well, &amp;ldquo;scientific&amp;rdquo;. There is Science of War, Science of Language, Science of Astronomy, Science of Living Beings, etc. If you have had an interest in Hinduism and spent anytime reading articles on it or following pages that post about Hinduism and it&amp;rsquo;s glory, you have likely come across the &amp;ldquo;Dashavatara-Evolution Theory&amp;rdquo;.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In Bharat, the religion developed along side the civilization. Hence, it is difficult to make any distinctions between the two. For this reason, Bharat&rsquo;s science is both religious and, well, &ldquo;scientific&rdquo;. There is Science of War, Science of Language, Science of Astronomy, Science of Living Beings, etc. If you have had an interest in Hinduism and spent anytime reading articles on it or following pages that post about Hinduism and it&rsquo;s glory, you have likely come across the &ldquo;Dashavatara-Evolution Theory&rdquo;. And on the surface, it makes a lot of sense. But does this fit well theologically?</p>
<p>For those unfamiliar with the theory, it goes this way: The ten great avatars of Bhagavan Vishnu represent human evolution, from sea dwelling organisms to peak enlightenment. Hence, the Matsya Avatara represents the micro-organism that evolved in water. Following the fish form, you have the Kurma Avatara which reprensents the adaptation of life to sustain itself on both land and water. Varaha Avatara repesents the complete evolution to land dwelling animal and Narsimha Avatara represents the transition of animal to man. The Vamana and &ldquo;Parshu&rdquo; Rama Avataras are supposed to represent the primitive man, while Ramachandra and Vasudeva Krishna are supposed to represent the civilized. Finally, the Buddha Avatara is humanity at it&rsquo;s height of intelligence and learning, waiting for the eventual decline that will be brought by Kalki Avatara. This seems very logical and &ldquo;scientific&rdquo;, right? Well, let&rsquo;s take a look.</p>
<p>The theory first assumes that Hinduism&rsquo;s concept of time is the same as how we percieve it now. There&rsquo;s a beginning, a middle, and then there&rsquo;s an end. After the end, we are not sure what happenes. But the theological explanation is that there is a beginning again. The time measurements range from a Kshana to Kalpa, which is a gigantic measurement of time according to which the &ldquo;scientific&rdquo; age of Earth is relatively very young. Not only that, time never ceases to exist, just as the Jivatma or the Paramatma. They are infinite. There is no beginning, there is no middle and there is no end here. Why do I bring this up? Well, because, by modern calculations, millions and millions of years elapse between successive avataras and they take place in not just different Mahayugas but also Manavantaras. Not only that, these ten reincarnations are just the most popular ones. The Bhagavata Purana mentions 22 avataras! If we keep the puranas aside for a while, the list still misses out on the Narayana avatara of Vishnu which predates both the Ramas (quite possibly Vamana too) and is mentioned countless times in the Mahabharata.</p>
<p>Then we must ask ourselves, what is the theory actually based on? Is it based on biology? Or morals and enlightenment? If it is based on biology, then one can stop at &ldquo;Parashu&rdquo; Rama (and Vamana too but let&rsquo;s put him aside since he was a dwarf and a defect can be pointed out) because he is not a &ldquo;primitive&rdquo; man, rather he is a hermit, a renunciate in many aspects. He is famous for the destruction of Sahasrabahu Kartavirya Arjuna, who was a king of a then strong kingdom. Not only that, the theory does not take into account Mohini avatara, which came to be about the same time as Kurma avatara. Mohini is the female reincarnation of Vishnu to decieve Asuras. No, the list cannot be based on biology then.</p>
<p>So it is based on morals and enlightenment? Ok, why should we not stop at Vamana then? Vamana, though child he was during his confrontation with Bali, later on went to establish many hermitages. Should he be not considered enlightened? Ramachandra is hailed as the best of the Ikshavaku dynasty and also one of the greatest kings to ever rule. His sacrifices and sufferings were for Dharma. Does he not have the most sacrosanct morality? What about Bhagavan Krishna then? Time after time, since his birth, he has been hailed as the being who sustains everything that exists. He was the one who imparted his teachings to the world through the Mahabharata. Or Krishna Dvaipayana Veda Vyasa, who did great serice to the Dharmic compositions and literature. Are they not enlightened beyond human conceptions then? Another thing to consider is that Siddhartha Gautama, the Buddha, was listed as an avatara of Vishnu much later on, much closer to our times.</p>
<p>If one finds delight in believing this theory, I am no one to change their minds. It does make a lot of sense at a strech. But as with most deeply religious things that people desperately try to explain with the modern scientific views, this one has many holes and is straight up wrong at times.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanatana Dharma: Religion or Civilization?</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/002-religionorciv/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 14:37:44 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/002-religionorciv/</guid>
      <description>History has always been a very intriguing subject. It&amp;rsquo;s a portal to the past based on imprints left by natural forces or great civilizations and subsequently great empires. While remnants left by natural forces help us understand the Earth, the ones by civilizations help us understand the man of the past. Their behavior, society, beliefs et cetera. Any read through of history, and you shall come around some common names. Such as Romans, Greeks, Egyptians, Chinese and the Indians.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>History has always been a very intriguing subject. It&rsquo;s a portal to the past based on imprints left by natural forces or great civilizations and subsequently great empires. While remnants left by natural forces help us understand the Earth, the ones by civilizations help us understand the man of the past. Their behavior, society, beliefs et cetera. Any read through of history, and you shall come around some common names. Such as Romans, Greeks, Egyptians, Chinese and the Indians. While smaller civilizations existed everywhere like in parts of South Iraq, earlier known as Sumeria or the indigenous society of then undiscovered North America, the ones mentioned earlier have had a massive impacts in their respective regions and sometimes even dictate the the traditions that have been passed down to the present. While it is debatable which civilization came first, a rather unwarranted debate actually because of the difference of regions and cultures, all these civilizations have existed for millennia. But none of the earlier civilizations have survived to witness the present world or have their ethics survived. All except the Indian, or the Dharmic civilization.</p>
<p>It is agreed upon the fact that the region of Indus Valley, or Sindh as the ancient Indians called it, is the cradle of Indian Civilization. The society was built upon the rivers Sindhu and Saraswati. Hence it is also referred to as &ldquo;Saraswati-Sindhu&rdquo; Civilization. The cities of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro were the first settlements of the civilization and have left their imprints not only in the area itself but other civilizations they had their relations with. Sometime later on, Rakhigarhi became central to the civilization. Now, a baseless argument and a great misconception is that some time later, these settlements &ldquo;vanished&rdquo; from the face of the Ancient India and soon after the &ldquo;Aryans invaded&rdquo; the Northern regions of the sub-continent &ldquo;bringing India it&rsquo;s culture&rdquo;. The Aryan Invasion theory has been debunked many times: archaeologically, genealogically, linguistically and all other -allies possible, and hence has been toned down to the &ldquo;Aryan Migration&rdquo; theory. What even? I will not shit on the theory here but you can just search for it on YouTube. You can watch these for starters: Presentation by Dr. Raj Vedam, Presentation by Dr. Abhijit Chavda and Panel Discussion about the theory.</p>
<p>With the stupid stuff out of the way, let&rsquo;s get to the point. The Hindu civilization has been one of the most powerful civilizations throughout history. This is indicated by the numerous historic records which were made obscure by Western historians for a long time. Indians dominated the whole of South-Eastern Asia including countries like the present day Afghanistan (referred to as Gandhara in Hindu texts), Pakistan, Nepal, Bangladesh and parts of Myanmar, Bhutan, Cambodia, Indonesia and Philippines in later periods. And of course, including the present day India. Not only that, the Dharmic ethics of ancient India have influenced religions other part of Eastern Asia. A moderate-read of ancient Hindu texts clearly point to the fact that religious philosophy and social order were intermixed with each other and one influenced the other. A few instances include the Itihasa texts of Indian literature. Ithasa literally means &ldquo;thus-it-happened&rdquo; in Sanskrit and are regarded to have historical authority. The two Itihasa texts, Ramayana and Mahabharata are not only some of the greatest stories ever told but also historical records of how the society was in their times. The other scriptures such as the Vedas and Puranas have their own historical authenticity but their theological side is embraced more than the historical. A thorough read-through the corpus of Hindu literature helps us imagine the civilization of the old. Their behaviors, society, beliefs et cetera.</p>
<p>But in the times of now, these practices have been just rendered as a religion. There is indeed truth to that attribution but Ethics of War, A Social Order through the Varna-Jaati System, The Rules of Ruling, Preservation of Nature et cetera are all non-religious aspects of the society which are derived from the theology itself. These all strive for Dharma, a very nuanced word whose meaning and never be captured by western languages. A disregard of the Vedic principles would mean disregarding the entire civilization. And it&rsquo;s not as if the Indian Civilization was weak. It is strong. Kings and Emperors commanded large armies and dominated large portions of the nation. Yes, indeed, there was a nation. There was no centralized government (rather there have been Emperors who dominated the ancient land), but there was a common culture. From north to south, the civilization followed common ethics and did only differ in the names of kingdoms. They followed Dharma.</p>
<p>The sciences, art forms, languages, laws and life-style of the common man all derive themselves from the Vedic truth. Of course, that&rsquo;s not to say literally every single thing has it&rsquo;s basis in the Vedas but the most important aspects do. And these traditions have survived the onslaught of various invasions and foreign corruptions. The credit for this lies with none other but the Indians themselves. Common folk preserving their ways of life, Kings preserving common folk, the Acharyas preserving the Vedas amongst other things contributed to the survival of the culture. It sought this as their Dharma.</p>
<p>To be born in this civilization and realize it&rsquo;s grandeur, I believe it is my Dharma contribute in any way I can. How about writing a blogs on this topic for starters, eh?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>