<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>history on Shrama</title>
    <link>https://raunackt.github.io/tags/history/</link>
    <description>Recent content in history on Shrama</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Raunack Tripathi</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2023 09:58:29 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raunackt.github.io/tags/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notes on first two chapters from Lokamanya Tilak&#39;s Orion</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/003-notes-on-orion-two-chaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2023 09:58:29 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/003-notes-on-orion-two-chaps/</guid>
      <description>At two instances in Mahābharata, Bhīṣma&amp;rsquo;s standard, the symbols of his flag are described. Once as five stars and sun (CE 4.3.50) and second as five stars and a palm tree (CE 6.4.44). We are not told the significance of these symbols, nor can we infer anything from within the story of Mahābhārata as to why Bhīṣma would have chosen them. Whatever can be guessed is with the knowledge of the larger vaidika mythology and in refernce to Dyaus Pitṛ, or simply Dyou in Mahābhārata, who is one of the 8 vasu-s who was cursed to be born as a mortal.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At two instances in Mahābharata, Bhīṣma&rsquo;s standard, the symbols of his flag are described. Once as five stars and sun (CE 4.3.50) and second as five stars and a palm tree (CE 6.4.44). We are not told the significance of these symbols, nor can we infer anything from <em>within</em> the story of Mahābhārata as to why Bhīṣma would have chosen them. Whatever can be guessed is with the knowledge of the larger <em>vaidika</em> mythology and in refernce to Dyaus Pitṛ, or simply Dyou in Mahābhārata, who is one of the 8 <em>vasu</em>-s who was cursed to be born as a mortal. Dyou was born as Bhīṣma, the son of Gaṇgā and Shantanu (CE 1.7.93). Dyaus and Bhīṣma share similarities in that they are both said to be a &ldquo;grandfather&rdquo; figure in their respective domains, are larger than life entities and for Bhīṣma specifically, he is one of the last remanents of older Kaurava-s who links with the Pāṇdava-s. It is on this backdrop that the five stars (and the one version with sun) start making sense: Bhīṣma is representing the sky on his standard, as that is his domain.</p>
<p>I had asked this question to a learned person, and he theorized that it might have something to do with the planets that were observed very early on, excluding the Sun and the Moon, viz., Venus, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn and possibly Mercury, though its proximity to the Sun makes it harder to spot. I inquired if this theory is based on a book which this individual adores very much, written by <em>Lokamānya</em> Tilak, titled <strong>&ldquo;The Orion Or Researches Into The Antiquity Of The Vedas&rdquo;</strong>. The book was published in 1893, during the same time in which many other books on Hindu cultural studies that were being translated into English after the British colonization had taken full effect were being published. Tilak himself postulates a date for the Veda-s, more specifically the <em>vaidika</em> texts such as <em>saṇhitā</em>-s, etc., using the internal astronomical (or astrological) references from these texts. The person said yes, but while I have found nothing related to the five stars/planets in the book so far, it is a fantastic and enlightening read nonetheless.</p>
<p>The accuracy of Tilak&rsquo;s work aside, the actual information within it is extremely useful, especially since such subjects are not discussed widely (any more atleast), owing to either unacceptance of non-traditional analysis of the <em>shāstra</em>-s or general ignorance. It comprises comments and discussions by various scholars, ancient and modern on these astronomical references and how they changed (or remained the same).</p>
<p>The cosmos is always in motion, which the concept of <em>ṛta</em> aptly conveys. The motions of the celestial bodies and seasons were very much understood by extremely ancient <em>ārya</em>-s, and they built their long-term rituals like the <strong><em>samvatsara satra</em></strong> accordingly. This is a <em>yajña</em> mentioned in the <em>Aitareya Brāhmaṇa</em>&rsquo;s 4th <em>pañcikā</em> and is described in enough detail for us to infer that the <em>satra</em> corresponded and extended to one whole year. It started on the beginning of a new year, and each major phase of the <em>yajña</em> lasted for 6 months, at which pont it was split by a <em>viṣuvantaḥ</em> or <em>viṣuvān</em>, and the ritual carried on for another 6 months until the end of the year.</p>
<p>What is fascinating about this is when exactly did the year begin in these ancient times. While today different regions celebrate beginning of a traditional new year in different months like <em>Āshvina</em> or <em>Kārtika</em> or <em>Caitra</em>, etc., it is generally accepted that 12 months are divided into <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> and <em>dakṣināyana</em>, which basically mean that the Sun travels northwards and southwards (in the sky) for a period of six months each. The day these transitions happen are called the solstices. Currently, there is a discrepancy as to when <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> actually begins, but it still does not indiciate the beginning of a new year.</p>
<p><em>Uttarāyaṇa</em> as a phase is associated with the time of <em>devatā</em>-s, and all auspicious ceremonies (like <em>upanayana saṇskāra</em>) are performed in this period. <em>Dakṣināyana</em> is associated with the time of <em>pitṛ</em>-s, or Yama and all funeral related ceremonies (<em>shrāddha</em>) are part of these 6 months. As it is right now, the seasons of <em>Shishira</em>, <em>Vasanta</em> and <em>Grīṣma</em> make the first phase and <em>Varṣā</em>, <em>Sharada</em> and <em>Hemanta</em> make the second. <strong>BUT</strong>, in <em>Shatapatha Brāhmaṇa</em>&rsquo;s 2nd <em>khaṇḍa</em>, we have the following <em>mantra</em>-s:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>वसन्तो ग्रीष्मो वर्षाः। ते देवा ऋतवः शरद्धेमन्तः शिशिरस्ते पितरो य एवापूर्यतेऽर्धमासः स देवा योऽपक्षीयते स पितरोऽहरेव देवा रात्रिः पितरः पुनरह्नः पूर्वाह्णो देवा अपराह्णः पितरः ।१।</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>ते वा एत ऋतवः। देवाः पितरः स यो हैवं विद्वान्देवाः पितर इति ह्वयत्या हास्य देवा देवहूयं गचन्त्या पितरः पितृहूयमवन्ति हैनं देवा देवहूये ऽवन्ति पितरः पितृहूये य एवं विद्वान्देवाः पितर इति ह्वयति ।२।</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>स यत्रोदगावर्तते। देवेषु तर्हि भवति देवांस्तर्ह्यभिगोपायत्यथ यत्र दक्षिणावर्तते पितृषु तर्हि भवति पितॄंस्तर्ह्यभिगोपायति ।३।</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>वसन्तो ग्रीष्मो वर्षाः। ते देवा ऋतवः शरद्धेमन्तः शिशिरस्ते पितरो</strong>, this part of <em>mantra</em> expressely states which seasons belong, or belonged, to which entity. The idea of these three months being the <em>devatā</em> seasons is essentially the same as <em>uttarāyaṇa</em> being the phase of the <em>devatā</em>-s. Same of the next three for <em>pitṛ</em>-s.</p>
<p>This is <em>only</em> possible when the year is divided along the equinoxes, the vernal and autumnal. The word <em>viṣuvantaḥ</em> from earlier is made up of &ldquo;<em>viṣu</em>&rdquo; (equally, on both sides) and &ldquo;<em>-vantaḥ</em>&rdquo; (full of, having), hence literally meaning &ldquo;having equal halves&rdquo;, which in terms of an year is a division of 6 months, and keeping inline with the above <em>mantra</em>-s, this division should happen at the equinoxes. We now have express testimony of ancient texts to strongly assert that very early on, the <em>vaidika</em>-s celebrated the beginning of a new year on the vernal equinox.</p>
<p><em>To be continued</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanatana Dharma: Religion or Civilization?</title>
      <link>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/002-religionorciv/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 14:37:44 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raunackt.github.io/blogs/002-religionorciv/</guid>
      <description>History has always been a very intriguing subject. It&amp;rsquo;s a portal to the past based on imprints left by natural forces or great civilizations and subsequently great empires. While remnants left by natural forces help us understand the Earth, the ones by civilizations help us understand the man of the past. Their behavior, society, beliefs et cetera. Any read through of history, and you shall come around some common names. Such as Romans, Greeks, Egyptians, Chinese and the Indians.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>History has always been a very intriguing subject. It&rsquo;s a portal to the past based on imprints left by natural forces or great civilizations and subsequently great empires. While remnants left by natural forces help us understand the Earth, the ones by civilizations help us understand the man of the past. Their behavior, society, beliefs et cetera. Any read through of history, and you shall come around some common names. Such as Romans, Greeks, Egyptians, Chinese and the Indians. While smaller civilizations existed everywhere like in parts of South Iraq, earlier known as Sumeria or the indigenous society of then undiscovered North America, the ones mentioned earlier have had a massive impacts in their respective regions and sometimes even dictate the the traditions that have been passed down to the present. While it is debatable which civilization came first, a rather unwarranted debate actually because of the difference of regions and cultures, all these civilizations have existed for millennia. But none of the earlier civilizations have survived to witness the present world or have their ethics survived. All except the Indian, or the Dharmic civilization.</p>
<p>It is agreed upon the fact that the region of Indus Valley, or Sindh as the ancient Indians called it, is the cradle of Indian Civilization. The society was built upon the rivers Sindhu and Saraswati. Hence it is also referred to as &ldquo;Saraswati-Sindhu&rdquo; Civilization. The cities of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro were the first settlements of the civilization and have left their imprints not only in the area itself but other civilizations they had their relations with. Sometime later on, Rakhigarhi became central to the civilization. Now, a baseless argument and a great misconception is that some time later, these settlements &ldquo;vanished&rdquo; from the face of the Ancient India and soon after the &ldquo;Aryans invaded&rdquo; the Northern regions of the sub-continent &ldquo;bringing India it&rsquo;s culture&rdquo;. The Aryan Invasion theory has been debunked many times: archaeologically, genealogically, linguistically and all other -allies possible, and hence has been toned down to the &ldquo;Aryan Migration&rdquo; theory. What even? I will not shit on the theory here but you can just search for it on YouTube. You can watch these for starters: Presentation by Dr. Raj Vedam, Presentation by Dr. Abhijit Chavda and Panel Discussion about the theory.</p>
<p>With the stupid stuff out of the way, let&rsquo;s get to the point. The Hindu civilization has been one of the most powerful civilizations throughout history. This is indicated by the numerous historic records which were made obscure by Western historians for a long time. Indians dominated the whole of South-Eastern Asia including countries like the present day Afghanistan (referred to as Gandhara in Hindu texts), Pakistan, Nepal, Bangladesh and parts of Myanmar, Bhutan, Cambodia, Indonesia and Philippines in later periods. And of course, including the present day India. Not only that, the Dharmic ethics of ancient India have influenced religions other part of Eastern Asia. A moderate-read of ancient Hindu texts clearly point to the fact that religious philosophy and social order were intermixed with each other and one influenced the other. A few instances include the Itihasa texts of Indian literature. Ithasa literally means &ldquo;thus-it-happened&rdquo; in Sanskrit and are regarded to have historical authority. The two Itihasa texts, Ramayana and Mahabharata are not only some of the greatest stories ever told but also historical records of how the society was in their times. The other scriptures such as the Vedas and Puranas have their own historical authenticity but their theological side is embraced more than the historical. A thorough read-through the corpus of Hindu literature helps us imagine the civilization of the old. Their behaviors, society, beliefs et cetera.</p>
<p>But in the times of now, these practices have been just rendered as a religion. There is indeed truth to that attribution but Ethics of War, A Social Order through the Varna-Jaati System, The Rules of Ruling, Preservation of Nature et cetera are all non-religious aspects of the society which are derived from the theology itself. These all strive for Dharma, a very nuanced word whose meaning and never be captured by western languages. A disregard of the Vedic principles would mean disregarding the entire civilization. And it&rsquo;s not as if the Indian Civilization was weak. It is strong. Kings and Emperors commanded large armies and dominated large portions of the nation. Yes, indeed, there was a nation. There was no centralized government (rather there have been Emperors who dominated the ancient land), but there was a common culture. From north to south, the civilization followed common ethics and did only differ in the names of kingdoms. They followed Dharma.</p>
<p>The sciences, art forms, languages, laws and life-style of the common man all derive themselves from the Vedic truth. Of course, that&rsquo;s not to say literally every single thing has it&rsquo;s basis in the Vedas but the most important aspects do. And these traditions have survived the onslaught of various invasions and foreign corruptions. The credit for this lies with none other but the Indians themselves. Common folk preserving their ways of life, Kings preserving common folk, the Acharyas preserving the Vedas amongst other things contributed to the survival of the culture. It sought this as their Dharma.</p>
<p>To be born in this civilization and realize it&rsquo;s grandeur, I believe it is my Dharma contribute in any way I can. How about writing a blogs on this topic for starters, eh?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>